<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lives, actions, and execution of the prime actors, and principall contrivers of that horrid murder of our late pious and sacred soveraigne, King Charles the First ... with severall remarkable passages in the lives of others, their assistants, who died before they could be brought to justice / by George Bate, an observer of those transactions.</title>
            <title>Elenchus motuum nuperorum in Anglia. English</title>
            <author>Bate, George, 1608-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5539</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11893358</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11893358</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50469</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26768)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50469)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 53:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lives, actions, and execution of the prime actors, and principall contrivers of that horrid murder of our late pious and sacred soveraigne, King Charles the First ... with severall remarkable passages in the lives of others, their assistants, who died before they could be brought to justice / by George Bate, an observer of those transactions.</title>
                  <title>Elenchus motuum nuperorum in Anglia. English</title>
                  <author>Bate, George, 1608-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 144 p. : ports.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Vere ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Regicides.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:50469:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Harriſon.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>I. Caren.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cooke.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Peters.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>T. Scott.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>O. Cromwell.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>Ad. Scroope.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50469:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:50469:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50469:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIVES, ACTIONS, AND EXECUTION OF The prime Actors, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Contrivers of that horrid Murder of our <hi>late pious</hi> and <hi>Sacred</hi> Soveraigne King CHARLES <hi>the firſt,</hi> of Ever bleſſed memory.</p>
            <p>WITH Severall Remarkable Paſſages in the Lives of others, their Aſſiſtants, who died before they could be brought to Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> GEORGE BATE, <hi>an obſerver of thoſe Tranſactions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Vere,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Angell</hi> without <hi>Newgate,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50469:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50469:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>James</hi> Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Earl of <hi>Brecknock,</hi> Lord High Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of his Majeſties Houſhold, Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Councel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Hope your Lordſhip will be pleaſed to pardon the Authors preſumption in his humble Dedication to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, of <hi>this ſmall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the prime
<pb facs="tcp:50469:4"/> Authors and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the moſt Horrid Murther that ever was committed in the Face of the Sun;</hi> For ſuch I am ſure your Lordſhip did alwaies account that of our late Soveraign, and ſuch likewiſe was it look't upon by all Truly and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Ingenious in the whole World.</p>
            <p>Farre be it from me to have the leaſt thought, that my mean Pen ſhould draw
<pb facs="tcp:50469:4"/> a Lively Repreſentation of <hi>his late Majeſties</hi> (both) <hi>naturall and acquired ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> ſhining with ſo much ſplendor through the Darke and thick Clouds of his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions; yet to the end the world might ſee the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Deſignes of theſe Miſerable Men, <hi>who ſo wickedly perſecuted our Soveraign like a</hi> Partridge <hi>upon the top of the Mountaines.</hi> I have at the cloſe hereof attempted ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:50469:5"/> that might make them appear the more Wicked, by how much they Murthered ſo Pious, ſo Incomparable a Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My LORD,</hi> You had your ſhare of the miſeries in thoſe times, and your Life was hunted after <hi>by theſe Blood-Hounds.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable paſſages of whoſe Lives and Deaths are here preſented to your Lordſhips View; this being but as an Eſſay to what hereafter ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:50469:5"/> be ſet forth in a greater Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume.</p>
            <p>And now may your Lordſhip Live to ſee Peace Flouriſh all your time, and may your Children inherit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Bleſſing thereof, as well as your outward ſubſtance; May your Lordſhips Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty (which cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded) be Copied out by them; and may the reward of your Fidelity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy be an immortall Crown when God ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:50469:6"/> take you to his owne King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips Humbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Devoted Servant,</hi> GEORGE BAT<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50469:6"/>
            <head>The Prooemium.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen it pleaſed Almighty God to turn again the Captivity of Sion, and to return with glory his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, to the undoubted Dominions of his Anceſtors, after a black and dark night of Confuſion, Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Rebellion; and (by his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing within this his own Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere) to diſpel and ſcatter all thoſe malignant Clouds which for twelve years together had beni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe three Nations; The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament thought it their duty in the behalf of the People of <hi>England,</hi> to make inquiſition for that ſacred and innocent blood which was ſhed in their names, and upon the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed accompt of their conſent: For
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50469:7"/> which purpoſe, a ſpecial Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Oyer and Terminer was iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Seſſions Houſe in the <hi>Old Baily</hi> appointed for their tria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation: Now the inten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this diſcourſe is to give a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Lives, Educations, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Deaths of the prime Actors an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> principal Contrivers of that horri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Murther of Butchering our late pi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous &amp; ſacred Sovereign King <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Firſt of ever bleſſed Memory wherein I cannot but premiſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prophetique expreſſion of that hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Man of God Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> when he was upon the Scaffold <hi>viz. That thoſe who had gotten pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by policy, and uſed it with cruelty, ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe it with ignominy,</hi> at the cloſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which words, Mr. <hi>Love</hi> was inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupted by Alderman <hi>Titchbourn,</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>riff of <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>don,</hi> who would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m to proceed; but the Alde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man hath ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce found it verified i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his own experience, having ſinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50469:7"/> changed his Chain of Gold, for Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers of Iron.</p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this deſign, many ſtrange and horrid conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were in debate; the original contrivers whereof were very few; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he firſt Cockatrice Egge that was hatcht in this wicked crew, was Lt. Col. <hi>Joyces</hi> ſeizing the King at <hi>Holmby,</hi> whereby he was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately taken from Major Gen. <hi>Brown,</hi> who then attended him by order of the Parliament; and tranſlated to the power and tyranny of a vicious and mercileſſe Army, and at that time (being but the proemium of the Kings afterwards unhap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y fate) it was the words of <hi>Cromwell</hi> to <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> by way of queſtion, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there could not be found a way to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Nation without the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g?</hi> To whom that miſerable wretch repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That there was no way to do it, but by taking off his head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> being thus the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50469:8"/> chief Actor in this ſad Tragedy and for that he received not the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward of his iniquity in this Worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but is conveyed to the immedia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Judgment of the all juſt God, ſhall only give you a brief Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cter of his Education and Life, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome notes and obſervations on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> was a man, to gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him his true Character, of val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the head of an Army, and wicked policy in the front of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Council; being born in <hi>Hunting</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Shire, and brought up in the Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> until his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bauched incivility, and ſottiſh i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſobriety expelled him that plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> He was ſo conſtant and lewd a Live at his firſt comming into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> World, that his wits in his afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> years was chiefly imployed to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up the breaches of the former; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which purpoſe he fore-ſaw tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there was no way to help his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cayed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50469:8"/> Eſtate, but by turning facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, upon which accompt, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſently appears a great Stickler <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt Monarchy and Epiſcopacy: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d preſently layes hold of the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>portunity to appear in Arms, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſed through all the degrees of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilitary imployment, until at laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e arived at General of the Army; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aving firſt ſupplanted or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ined all honeſter men that ſtood in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is way, wading to the Government <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f theſe Nations over head and ears <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> blood; for having firſt ſpilt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnocent blood of our Sovereign, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd polluted his ſoul therewith, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ares not to ſpill the blood of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ubjects like water, plenty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f was ſhed in our ſtreets, during <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ſhort and troubleſome Reign, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is oppreſſion, diſſimulation, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and cruelty: When he was owned by a few to be Protector, he called ſeveral Parliaments, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting that they would throw that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50469:9"/> Title and the Government of theſe Nations upon him; but this way would not do, for though he nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated the very men that ſhould fit in ſome Parliaments, and ſent his private letters to have his own creatures choſen in others; yet he could not be eſtabliſhed by them, which occaſioned that his deſperate expreſſion at the diſſolving one of his Parliaments, <hi>That he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be roled in blood with infamy to his grave, then ſurrender up that power which God and the People had put upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1656, a Parliament was called, and indeed his laſt; where none were ſuffered to ſit, but ſuch as would ſign to own his uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; and one day, when about a hundred and odde ſate, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part whereof were either his own ſervants, alliance, or friends, he is voted King (as ſome of them have ſaid ſince, only to ſet him upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50469:9"/> that tickliſh pinacle, that ſo his fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight be the greater) but the Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not endure that title which ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tely they had buried with ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>retetended ſeeking of God, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe called hypocriſie and mocking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God; but yet he accepts of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ignity, preheminence and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence of a King in all reſpects what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oever, and acts as one accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngly.</p>
            <p>But here his heart is broke, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ingratiate himſelf with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, mittigates the Tax, although his expence increaſed, the publike Aſſeſment is reduced from 120 to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hreeſcore thouſand pounds <hi>per men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em,</hi> and the charge of the Navy and Army continues as before, whereby he ran much behind hand with them both; and in the mean time the King our now gracious Sovereign began to revive in the hearts of the people, ſeveral ſums of money are ſent him out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50469:10"/> of which <hi>Oliver</hi> gets intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, then he begins to contrive plots, many innocents are drawn in, Dr. <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> innocent lamb, with others, are devoured by this raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wolfe, the Gen ry all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over are diſturbed and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, and all things now begin to be in a ſtrange confuſion; he ſends for the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of <hi>London,</hi> and to them Crocodile like he weeps and tels a ſtory of the Kings preparation on the other ſide the water, that a great plot had been deſigning againſt him to the imbrewing the Nation again in blood, with other ſtrange ſtories never thought of, before he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived them himſelf; and now like the Devil he began to rave and tear when he perceived his Kingdom to be at an end; and at laſt having a Jury of diſtempers in him, all concentring together at one time to agonize that wicked body that had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50469:10"/> been the Author of ſo much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hief and Murther, he died on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hird of <hi>September</hi> 1658, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough he had at that time the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mnization of a Funeral fit for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of <hi>England,</hi> yet his ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us Statue and the mock Pomp of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at dayes glory was ſoon turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhame and diſgrace, by his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouldiers and friends, who (now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the change of Government from <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ichard</hi> his Son to the Rump Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent:) defaced and deſtroyed that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tate wherein he was ſet up in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Abbey, and converted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Protectorſhip into a more ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilous diſparagement, then that of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne of his meaneſt Souldiers. We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill take leave of this Monſter, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome to ſome of his wicked Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors, only will leave this Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cription to be engraven on his Tomb (if he be thought worthy of one.)</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50469:11"/>
               <l>Here lies ignominious duſt,</l>
               <l>Which was the only ſeat of luſt;</l>
               <l>A man and yet a Monſter too,</l>
               <l>That did both King and State undo;</l>
               <l>Moſt people ſay, this is his doom,</l>
               <l>That here he don't deſerve a Tomb.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50469:11"/>
            <head>The Life of Ma. Gen. <hi>Thomas Harriſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving given you a ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the General of this black A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>my; the next whoſe picture ſhall be preſented to you, is Maj. General <hi>Harriſon,</hi> a great Canter in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and a principal Header of the Fifth Monarchy Profeſſors. He was born at <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> under line in the County of <hi>Stafford,</hi> of very mean parents, although he afterwards ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to a very conſiderable Eſtate: being gained chiefly by the miſeries of the times, and the hypocriſie of his pretended preaching. His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was a Butcher, who brought him (according unto his ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>litie unto
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50469:12"/> Learning, and after a while placed him with one Mr. <hi>Hulk,</hi> an Attourney of <hi>Cliffords</hi> Inn. But, what ever the matter was, he deſired to live rather by the ruines, than by the practice of the Law: For not long after, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himſelf from his Pen to the Sword, and ſo inſinuated himſelf with the deluded Army, that he paſt from one command to another, till at laſt he attained to be Major General of <hi>Wales;</hi> in which imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to characterize his tyrannie, would ſwell to a volumn far exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this intended Diſcourſe. The Laws of the Land were not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Wales,</hi> but Major General <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons</hi> Laws were there in full force. No Orthodox Miniſter could there be ſuffered, but whom he pleaſed to allow; and with the aſſiſtance of his Chaplain Mr. <hi>Vavaſor Powel,</hi> (a giddy headed Parſon, and ſecond Brother to <hi>H. Peters</hi>) he endeavour'd the modeling of that Countrey, ſo,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50469:12"/> as that none but their own proſelytes ſhould teach and inſtruct the people. In a word, he was the chief <hi>Holden forth</hi> to that dangerous people called Fifth Monarchiers, and the chief Incendiary to ſet on foot, malignant and evil deſigns againſt that ſacred Inſtitution of Kings and Princes; and one that upon the trial of our moſt innocent Sovereign, uſed this expreſſion, <hi>That they ſhould blacken that white perſon as much as they could, in drawing up their charge againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the time of the Murther of our ſaid Soveraign, he was in great reputation with the Armie; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he was ſeveral times intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the Kings perſon, during that wicked confinement: He brought him from the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> to <hi>Windſor,</hi> and there had the charge of his perſon: And it was reported to the King at that time, That this Major General <hi>Harriſon</hi> had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign on foot to murther him private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50469:13"/> Which upon <hi>Harriſons</hi> trial, he denied, ſaying, That the King did once task him with ſuch a thing, but would not believe it when he ſaw his countenance: and that the King ſaid unto him, If thoſe perſons had been preſent that brought him ſuch a report, he would give them the lie, for that he himſelf had ſome skill in Phyſiognomy, and perceived in his face better principles.</p>
            <p>When the King was brought to his trial, this <hi>Harriſon</hi> was every day at that bloody Court; he was at all the private meetings for carrying on that wicked Act; he was at the conſultations for drawing up that horrid Charge; he was one who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the time, the place, and the manner of the Kings Execution; and he was lying in the bed with <hi>Ireton</hi> in a Chamber in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> where <hi>Cromwell</hi> lay: Likewiſe, when thoſe Miſcreants contrived a Sub-warrant to murther the King, which was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50469:13"/> drawn up by <hi>Cromwell</hi> for <hi>Hacker</hi> to ſigne, that morning when this unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel'd act was done.</p>
            <p>He continued one of the Darlings of that Rump Parliament, untill the year 1653. about which time they began to think of a New Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative, as they then called it.</p>
            <p>But Maj. General <hi>Harriſon</hi> contents not himſelf with the illegal power of the Rump Parliament; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires with <hi>Cromwell</hi> for their diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, although by his own confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in <hi>Newgate,</hi> it happened other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, which take as followeth.</p>
            <p>That morning that <hi>Cromwell</hi> went to diſſolve them, being the 23. of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril,</hi> 1653. he called <hi>Harriſon</hi> to go along with him; which he did, and as he pretended at that time, not knowing his deſign: But coming with him into the Parliament-houſe; and obſerving the diſorder he put them into, by reaſon of his intention to diſſolve them, he began to think
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50469:14"/> that thoſe Members intended to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate themſelves; and that there were others, whom, he ſaid, God would finiſh his work by: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſided with <hi>Cromwell,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the Speaker to come out of his Chair: but he ſaid, he would not come out, unleſs he were pull'd out: to which <hi>Harriſon</hi> ſaid, Sir, I will lend you my hand; which the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker giving him, he came out of his Chair, and ſo that piece of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were then interrupted.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Cromwell</hi> now ſeeing the way was layd open for himſelf to uſurp; and having kill'd to take poſſeſſion, puts <hi>Harriſon</hi> upon the work of diſſolving that mock Parliament: which being done, they now contrive which way to call ſuch a Parliament as would do what they pleaſed: and this was that which was called the praying Parliament, of which <hi>Praiſe-God Bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone</hi> was a Member. Theſe were not choſen by the Countrey, but by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50469:14"/> 
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> and <hi>Harriſon,</hi> but after they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad played with the Gove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo or three months, theſe were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ikewiſe in like manner diſſolved.</p>
            <p>And now theſe two ſtand in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition, who ſhould be greateſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his earthly Kingdom. But <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> having an Over-vote with the Officers of the Army, gets the head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Harriſ n,</hi> and will either make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im bow to his deſigns, or break <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im in pieces: which <hi>Harriſon</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to do, lays down his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Command together; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as ever after the Uſurpers Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, being carried from Caſtle to Caſtle through moſt parts of the Nation, like an exiled Malefactor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n which condition he continued for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome years, untill he was releaſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the Rump Parliament, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otwithſtanding he would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nowledg, but looks for the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Reign of our Saviour upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50469:15"/>
            <p>There was little more obſervable in the paſſages of his Life, but what were immediate forerunners of his Death. Maj. G. <hi>Lambert</hi> having made an eſcape from the Tower, had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged ſome factious perſons in the Countrey, of which this <hi>Harriſon</hi> was one, to raiſe Forces againſt the King, who was now voiced in moſt parts of the Nation, to be returning home. But <hi>Harriſon</hi> was taken in the very point of time, wherein he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have headed a Party, and was brought Priſoner to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> where he continued ſome months before he was arraigned in the <hi>Old Baily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He being brought to the Bar, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to flight and unconcern himſelf in the Tryal; his Conſcience being feared, was not at all penitent for being inſtrumental in ſhedding the innocent bloud of that pious Prince: But ſaying, That although other Kings had been privately aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50469:15"/> yet what he had done was in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e face of the Sun, and in the fear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Lord. He was found guilty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y his Jury, and was condemn'd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hang'd, drawn and quartered.</p>
            <p>On Saturday the 13 day of <hi>October,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was brought from <hi>New-gate;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ucted by a Troop of horſe and ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Trained Bands, and attended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the Sheriffs Officers, being drawn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a Sledg through the ſtreets to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hairing-Croſs:</hi> where a Gallows was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ected for his execution. All the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay as he went, he endeavoured to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcover to the world the undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edneſs of his ſpirit, by the ſmiles of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is countenance; which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding would not do: for he betrayed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelf much fear by an agony of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wet, and the more than ordinary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>embling and ſhaking of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oynts.</p>
            <p>Being come to the Gallows, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcended the Ladder, where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pake to the following effect: That
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50469:16"/> all that had been done in the late War, was by the ſtrange and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Providence of Almighty God; That all the Windings and Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that had been ſeen in the late Changes had been ordered and contrived by the ſame Providence; That by this Providence he was drawn in to be an unhappy Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Kings Death; And the ſame all wiſe-diſpoſing Providence had brought him to that End.</p>
            <p>After he had ſpake a little time to the ſame purpoſe, he went to Prayers; and then began to make himſelf ready for the Executioner. He bare up his ſpirits as much as could be, to flight Death, having taken a ſtrong Cordiall in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to that purpoſe. His laſt words were, That now he was going to the Lord Jeſus, and ſhould at the laſt Day, come again with him i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Glory, to judg the Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Earth, and thoſe that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50469:16"/> been his Judges. He was not ſo much thrown off the Ladder by the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner, but went as readily off himſelf. After which, the ſentence was executed upon him; his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers were cut off, and with his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els burnt; his Head was ſevered from his body, and on <hi>Tueſday</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet on <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall Gate; and his four Quarters were ordered to be ſet upon the Gates of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus ended He, that did betray</l>
               <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s King and Countrey; made a prey</l>
               <l>Of Law and Goſpel, and did ſpend</l>
               <l>His chiefeſt skill to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an end</l>
               <l>To Kingly Power, and throw down</l>
               <l>Both the Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itle and his Crown.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50469:17"/>
            <head>The Life of Colonel <hi>Iohn Iones.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>COllonel <hi>John Jones,</hi> came of mean Family in <hi>Wales,</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man of no repute before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Warre; he was ſent up to <hi>Londo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to be an Apprentice, but was pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced as a Serving-man to a Gentl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man; and afterwards was prefer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to Sir <hi>Thomas Middleton</hi> Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> with whom h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lived many years in the ſaid capaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty; but the Warres comming on, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like the reſt thought it would b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good fiſhing in troubled waters, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> went forth at the beginning of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Warres a Captain of foot, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his factious principles, which at tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50469:17"/> time was the only way to get into preferment, he was taken notice of, and was countenanced and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Cromwelian party; by reaſon whereof he was choſen a Parliament man in an abſent place, and by degrees came to be made Governour of <hi>Angleſey</hi> in <hi>North Wales,</hi> and ſeveral other ſucceſſive imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: And now the ſame party thirſting after the blood of the King, this <hi>John Jones</hi> is made a chief inſtrument in proſecuting that horrid Murther, and an eminent blood-hound in purſuing this inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent game; he ſet his hand to the Act for conſtituting that Court of Injuſtice, and likewiſe ſigned and ſealed that black warrant for the Execution; for which ſervice he gained more and more in the eſteem of thoſe wretched men, and was ſuddenly after ſent with <hi>Corbet, Ludlow,</hi> &amp;c. one of the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of Parliament: (ſo called)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50469:18"/> for the Government of <hi>Ireland,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which place it is admirable to thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with what ſtate and tyranny he ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed himſelf, perſecuting all tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were contrary to his principles, ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king up old Laws concerning th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brewing of Beer and Ale, and pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting them in execution with rigour plaguing all the houſes in <hi>Dubli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that ſold drink, and not ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any one to be in any publique im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ployment, that was ſeen to go int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an Ale-houſe; by which means pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple were forced to bugger Ale-hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and Taverns, and to go in at bac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doores; and on the other hand, tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing all out of imployment that wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not of the ſame Church with him diſcountenancing Orthodox Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, &amp; encouraging Mr. <hi>Patients,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a Stocking-footer in <hi>London</hi> to preach every Sunday before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Council of <hi>Ireland</hi> in <hi>Chriſt-Church Dublin;</hi> finally, to go into an Ale-houſe or a Proteſtant Church, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50469:18"/> his domination, were crimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike, and alike puniſhed; inſomuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat none but <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Welſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en</hi> were entertained at that time in beneficial places.</p>
            <p>News hereof was brought to <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Cromwell,</hi> who by this time had aſſumed the Protectorſhip, and a way is contrived by him to get Col. <hi>Jones</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> but ſo as not to give him occaſion of offenſe: which accordingly was done; for he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent over with ſome Papers to <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> but was never ſent back again by him with an Anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>He being a Man of an active ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, would not go off the Stage thus: out plays another game to ingratiate himſelf with the Protector, and ſo to come into favour again. For which purpoſe he marries a Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi>'s own Siſter; conceiving, that he marrying into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat Family, he might take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50469:19"/> and lay hold of opportunities a the Court for the preferring of him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf: but this likewiſe proved ineffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctual, for he never raiſed himſelf on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtep higher by this conjugal Tie, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onely to be one of thoſe Muſhroo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lords, which <hi>Cromwell</hi> made out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the meaneſt of the People. Whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mock honour his Lordſhip did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> long enjoy, for ſoon after <hi>Cromwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> dying, and he being one of his diſ-ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liged kinred, made it his buſineſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unpin the frame of that new mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Government, whereby the rubbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>afters fell upon their own hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and limbs; he being one of the chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſupplanters of his Cozen <hi>Richar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cromwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This exploit being thus accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pliſhed, he is now very active <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Wallingford</hi>-houſe, for bringing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Rump again; which ſucceedin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> according to his expectation, he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> again made one of the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners for the Government of <hi>Irelan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50469:19"/> with the aforenamed perſons. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent over again in <hi>July</hi> 1659, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ievt. Gen. <hi>Ludlow,</hi> who was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief of the Forces: and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udlow</hi> coming back again, left this Col. <hi>John Jones</hi> his Deputy there; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho being now <hi>Dominus fac totum,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts as rigorouſly as ever: which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>range kind of carriage of his, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teele,</hi> then Chancellor of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an of as haughty a ſpirit as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf) could not brook: For finding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imſelf overtopt by one whom he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hought much his inferior; he very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>airly left <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent thereof to this aſpiring <hi>Phaeton,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho ſuddenly after run them all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto confuſion.</p>
            <p>By this time the Rump Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent was turned out again, by <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ert,</hi> and a Committee of Safety have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow the Government toſt into their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſpoſe. With theſe Colonel <hi>John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ones</hi> preſently ſtrikes in, and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th their power by a Declaration
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50469:20"/> from <hi>Ireland.</hi> But here this Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <hi>Jack</hi> was ſoon dethroned For on the 6. of <hi>December</hi> following about five of the clock in the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Col. Sir <hi>Theophilus Jones,</hi> Col<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Bridges,</hi> and two or three more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced Officers, in purſuance of a Deſign very privately contrive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and carryed on, ſiezed on Col. <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jones,</hi> and the reſt of the then Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Ireland,</hi> took the Caſtle of <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> and declared for a Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Gen. <hi>Monck,</hi> who was then it <hi>Scotland,</hi> and had declared for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like. This Col. <hi>Jones</hi> is kept cloſe Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and the Rump Parliament getting into the ſaddle again, ſend for him and the reſt over: but by that time he was come to Town, the Secluded Members had admittance into the Houſe, by reaſon whereof, nothing was done againſt him at that time.</p>
            <p>And ſuddenly after, preparation being made for the Kings coming
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50469:20"/> home, Col. <hi>Jones</hi> hides himſelf; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otwithſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his concealment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was diſcovered one Evening a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out twilight, in <hi>Finsbury</hi> fields near <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ondon,</hi> and apprehended, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed Priſoner to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here he remained till he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought to his Tryal.</p>
            <p>The twelfth of <hi>October</hi> 1660, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as brought with the reſt to the Old <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayly,</hi> and his Bedfellow, Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing immediately tried before, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound guilty, he thought it was but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n vain to plead, for that their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were the ſame, which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad contrived to anſwer their Charge: and ſo he was ſoon found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uilty.</p>
            <p>And on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> following, he with others were drawn on a hurdle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Charing-Croſs</hi> aforeſaid, where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pake to the following effect: That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e did now ſee what he had often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieved, <hi>viz.</hi> That it was the Power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat made the Law, for that ſome
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50469:21"/> years before they had the power i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their hands, and whatſoever the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did at that time, was accounted La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and executed accordingly; Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now the King had executed the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon them, and that the King di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nothing but what he would hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> done himſelf, were he in the King caſe: For the King did but like a lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving and dutiful Son to a dear an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loving Father. After a ſmall pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, he committed his Soul into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hands of God, ſeemingly peniten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and was quartered as before.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Go thou time-ſerving Serving-man,</l>
               <l>Take thy reward from <hi>Dun,</hi> that can</l>
               <l>Beſt pay thee; one who will be ſure</l>
               <l>Thy utmoſt payment to procure.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Exit Jack,</hi> without applauſe,</l>
               <l>And bid adiew to th' Good Old Cauſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50469:21"/>
            <head>The Life of Maſter <hi>Iohn Cooke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MR. <hi>John Cooke,</hi> a man of very good natural parts, had they been employed to the purpoſe for which God gave them; Was of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n inconſiderable birth, and of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mall and mean Fortune: however, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y his miſsimployed policy, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old attempt of being Sollicitor in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he cauſe againſt the King, in that wicked Court of Injuſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; He was afterwards preferred to be a Judg in <hi>Ireland:</hi> by which, and other ways, he arrived to a conſiderable Eſtate.</p>
            <p>The firſt notice or mention which I find of him is, that he was a Barriſter
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50469:22"/> 
               <hi>Grays</hi> Inn, but had very little or n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> practice, and ſuch men were adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fit for the proſecution of that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Murther; who like <hi>Judas</hi> would betray their Lord for Thirty pieces of ſilver, which was the reward of his iniquity.</p>
            <p>The Rump Parliament about the 10. of <hi>January</hi> 1648, after they had made an Act for conſtituting a High Court of Juſtice, directed an Order to this M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cook,</hi> together with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ask</hi> and <hi>Doriſlaus,</hi> to draw up a Charge againſt his Majeſty, in which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cook</hi> was very active, and was the man that ſubſcribed that wicked Libel in the behalf of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> (who diſowned that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Murther,) and therein called his innocent Majeſty, Murtherer and Traytor, and therefore prayed Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice againſt him as ſuch a perſon; ſaying, That the bloud that had been ſpilt, cried for it. When the King was brought before thoſe bloudy miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50469:22"/> M<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Cook</hi> ſtood up and made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> long Speech to them againſt the King, according to the aforeſaid Charge; and when the King began <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſpeak any thing by way of anſwer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e would interrupt him. He did often complain to the Court, that the King trifled away time. He moved, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat if the King would not plead to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat wicked Charge, the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ained therein might be taken <hi>pro con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſo:</hi> and the laſt day he demanded Judgment of the Court againſt the Priſoner at the Bar, (which was the title he gave the King of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.) Upon which ſentence paſſed, and the horrid murther was ſoon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after the ſame,</p>
            <p>And it is to be obſerved, That this M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cook</hi> was at that time prickt in Conſcience, by the expreſſion which he uſed to an old friend of his, diſcourſing with whom about the Kings Death, he ſaid, That the King was a wiſe and a gracious Prince;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50469:23"/> but he muſt die, and Monarchy wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him.</p>
            <p>And now having had a finger i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this innocent bloud, he was reſolved to plunge himſelf over head and ears therein; for preſently after he writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Book intituled, <hi>Monarchy no creatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Gods making,</hi> and therein ſays, That the late King (meaning our bleſſed Soveraign King CHARLS the Firſt) was the fatteſt Sacrifice that ever was offered to Queen Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things made the Rump Parliament begin to think of a way to reward him; and Ordered him as the thanks of the Houſe, 300 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> in the County of <hi>Waterford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> whither they ſent him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and made him a Judg of that Law, which himſelf, contrary to his Oath, his Conſcience, and his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, had thus traiterouſly and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly broken and offended.</p>
            <p>He was not long in <hi>Ireland,</hi> before the Commiſſioners for Government
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50469:23"/> of <hi>Ireland</hi> made choice of him as the chief Judg to examine, try and give ſentence upon the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> according to ſuch Qualifications, as a pretended Act of that Rump Parliament had made and allowed, and to tranſplant whom they pleaſed, into <hi>Connaught:</hi> ſome for their murther of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and others for their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded delinquency in aſſiſting of the King: For which action I have heard his moderation much commended.</p>
            <p>During the time of his being thus a Judg, he was ſmitten with ſudden checks of Conſcience, which often made him, even upon the Bench, to fall into ſtrange ſighs and groans, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing his ſorrow for the Death of the King; and hath been often ſeen to ſtrike his breaſt, which was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with a groan, and then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed this expreſſion, <hi>Ah poor Charls, poor Charls!</hi> As if the guilt of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bloud lay heavy upon his Soul, and tormented him with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50469:24"/> continual and renewed diſturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>He continued in <hi>Ireland</hi> for ſome years, during which time he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up and down the Country; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> and at laſt, the Government changing, he was fiezed upon in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſent by the Parliament or Convention there, unto the Council of <hi>England,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the juſt puniſhment of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits. Being brought to <hi>London,</hi> he was immediately ſent to the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, where he remained ſome time, untill he was brought to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and received a fair Tryal in the Old <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon his Plea before the Court, he expreſſed himſelf with ſuch Law &amp; Learning, that the Judg applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame, ſaying, That he was very ſorry to ſee, that one that underſtood the Law ſo much, ſhould tranſgreſs it ſo much. It was proved againſt him, That he often interrupted the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50469:24"/> King in his Anſwers to that Court, and did uſe many unhandſom and uncivil expreſſions towards the King, all the time of that wicked Tryal; he being one of the loudeſt-mouth'd Bloud-hounds that purſued that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Lamb-like Prince, in a full cry, all thoſe days in which he was brought before them. The Jury that were upon him, went not out of the Court, but ſuddenly found him guilty.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Tueſday</hi> following he was Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to die at <hi>Chairing Croſs.</hi> He was now as penitent at his Death, as formerly he had expreſſed himſelf in his life. He was drawn upon a hurdle from <hi>Newgate</hi> to <hi>Chairing-Croſs</hi> aforeſaid; all the way as he went, lifting up his hands and his eyes, he would often turn his face towards the people, deſiring them to pray for him. Being come to the aforeſaid place, he went up the Ladder very penitently and chearfully; he told
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50469:25"/> the Sheriff, That as for himſelf, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thanked God, he could welcom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Death: but as for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> (who wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to die with him) he could very well have wiſhed that he might be reprei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for ſome time, for that he was neither prepared nor fit to die.</p>
            <p>He ſaid little as to the making of a Speech, but prayed moſt earneſtly and with affection both for the King and people: which be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng done, the Executioner did his Office, and being quartered, his Head was Ordered to be ſet on <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall, and his Limbs were ſent to be ſet upon the Gates of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Law lies a bleeding; Monarchy</l>
               <l>Expires; ſure then the Law muſt dy.</l>
               <l>But both revive, and <hi>Cook</hi> is made</l>
               <l>A ſad example to his Trade.</l>
               <l>His Head ſtands as a fair Take-heed,</l>
               <l>How they the bounds of Law exceed.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:50469:25"/>
            <head>The Life of Maſter <hi>Hugh Peters.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> a man of a continued tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent ſpirit, and as it is generally repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, little better than frantick: One that as he was a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Abettor and Encourager of all turbulent principles: ſo he particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly improved them in that horrid Act of the Kings murther.</p>
            <p>He was brought up, as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, in the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and from thence (having taken his Degrees) he ſet up the trade of an itinerary Preacher, never being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant or fixt to any one place or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50469:26"/> and roved about the world, like an univerſal Church-man, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Jeſuits: for ſometimes he was in <hi>New-England;</hi> ſometimes in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> &amp; about the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non here in <hi>England,</hi> where he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that his tender conſcience could not be yoked to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor ſubmit to the Order and Government of the Biſhops.</p>
            <p>When theſe unhappy Wars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan within theſe at that time unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Nations, this <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſhew himſelf a forward Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diary, to ſtir up and animate all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious and diſcontented perſons, now to appear and vindicate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and children from the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Prelatical Tyranny; and perſuaded ſuch whoſe heads were as giddy and whimſical as his own, That it was the Lords Cauſe, and that now he was carrying on his own work among them.</p>
            <p>When the Parliament had raiſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50469:26"/> Forces, he goes out Chaplain to a Regiment, and many times appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed a Captain in Arms himſelf, he preached the Souldiers into courage, to maintain and juſtifie their Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and by wicked and abſurd compariſons would tell the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, That Heaven was full of Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coats that had been killed in that Cauſe; and that all they that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the ſame, ſhould arrive at the like happineſs. It would be too tedious to inſert the many frenzical and frenetick humours, which this prophane Prophet uſed during the time of the Armies tyrannical do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and how the more poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick chief Officers have laughed in their ſleeves to ſee this ſad wretch abuſe both the Scriptures and the Souldiers too, with his wicked and ſcandalous interpretations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>When the King was ſiezed at <hi>Holmby,</hi> by the damnable impudence
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50469:27"/> of a till that time mean and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Officer, he was the firſt man that ever was heard to make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings Death, or for ought I know, ſo much as to imagine it. He was at the ſeveral meetings with <hi>Cromwell, Ireton, Harriſon,</hi> and thoſe other few perſons that contrived it privately among themſelves at the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Colemanſtreet,</hi> and the <hi>Nags head</hi> over againſt <hi>Baſinghall ſtreet;</hi> he prepared the People and Souldiers by Sermons for that wicked mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and made uſe of his Calling (wherein he ſhould have been the Miniſter of Peace) to be the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter of Treaſon. Afterwards when the King was at <hi>Windſor,</hi> he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the wicked Council of the Army, at the hatching of this Deſign; and when they brought the King from thence to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> he rode before him audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly like his Almoner.</p>
            <p>This wicked Jeſuitical Prieſt,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50469:27"/> was the onely buſie man, that dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted how and where the Act for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing the High Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſhould be proclaimed; which done, he ſaid, That there was a day a coming, (meaning that day when the King ſhould be murthered) that the Saints had been for many years a praying for. And when that bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Court ſate, he uſed this expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That he could even reverence them, their ſitting did ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the great day of Judgment, and the tryal of the whole world, which ſhould then be performed by the Saints.</p>
            <p>And now M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> begins not onely as a private perſon, but as a Miniſter, to proſecute this worſt of Evils. For the next day after the Court of that Injuſtice ſate, he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at <hi>Whitehall</hi> before that grand Tyrant <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> and for his Text took that then abuſed place of Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. the three laſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50469:28"/> verſes; <hi>To bind their Kings in chains, and their Nobles in fetters of iron: This honour have all the Saints,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Murther of the King is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and now <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> runs on to make Divinity the handmaid of his Deviliſh Doctrine: For the next <hi>Sunday</hi> after that abominable Fact was committed, he preaches again, and took his Text, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14.18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>All the Kings of the Nations, even all of them lie in glory, every one in his own houſe. But thou art caſt out of thy grave, like an abominable branch: and as the rayment of thoſe that are ſlain, thruſt through with a ſword, that go down to the ſtones of the pit, as a carcaſe troden under feet. Thou ſhalt not be joyned with them in burial</hi> &amp;c. Upon the top of the margin whereof was written, <hi>The Tyrants fall.</hi> And in his Application of that mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreted Text, he compared the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> all the time of which odious compariſon, <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſate before him
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50469:28"/> laughing, not being able to forbear the ſame, to ſee this wicked Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Devils, thus plauſibly and confidently to avouch and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this helliſh practice.</p>
            <p>The next occurrence which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened during theſe ſtrange tranſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, was the Parliaments appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> to be Lord Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to reduce the Earl of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Lord <hi>In chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin,</hi> to the obedience of that Rump Parliament: Who is appointed his Companion, but M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> and he muſt be the immediate Chaplain to the Devils Champion. In this Expedition for <hi>Ireland,</hi> it was ſtrange and almoſt wonderful to think how God curſt them with ſucceſs, and how ſuddainly that Nation, which had ſo long groaned with the dayly effuſion of bloud, was within the ſpace of a year or a little more, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to that uſurped power: Here M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> adviſed them to make
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50469:29"/> ſhort work of the buſineſs, and by giving an example to the ſtrongeſt Garriſon, they might thereby frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the whole Nation: Purſuant whereunto, <hi>Tredagh</hi> was ſtormed, and although Quarter was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet none was given, and 4500 ſouls were there butchered; moſt of which were <hi>Engliſh</hi> and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. Which cruel Act, giving an allarm to the whole Countrey, cauſed the reſt to ſurrender upon Articles.</p>
            <p>About the year 1656. when <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> had aſſumed the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> is a great Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier &amp; a continual Aſſerter and Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator of his Uſurpation: but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it came to paſs, <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> is preſently out of favour, becauſe he had too far courted a Court-Lady, &amp; as ſome ſay, his active ſpirit had carnally known her: hereupon <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> grows litrle better than ſtark mad, raves like a <hi>Bedlamite,</hi> and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50469:29"/> ſhews himſelf much more void of ſenſe, than ever he was before: yet notwithſtanding, for the wicked ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice he had done, and for the further more damnable ſervices which they expected he might, he was again dub'd a favorite to his aforeſaid wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Patron.</p>
            <p>Finally, in the begining of the laſt year of <hi>Olivers</hi> Tyranny, <hi>Dunkirk</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now beſieged, and every day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be taken, <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> is ſent over to encourage the Souldiers as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his former wont had been, and being landed upon the Sands of <hi>Flanders,</hi> he immediately fell down upon his knees, and hypocritically praying, told the Souldiers, That he had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from God, that they were to be the Inſtruments of making his name known to the utmoſt parts of the earth.</p>
            <p>Preſently after <hi>Oliver</hi> dies, and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> preaching the next day in the Chappel at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> took his Text
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50469:30"/> in <hi>Deuteronomy, My Servant Moſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dead:</hi> The drift of his Sermon being to make out <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> equall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Servant of God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been.</p>
            <p>And here ends the further mentio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Prophet, for Governmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ever and anon afterwards being ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from one factious party to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at laſt all proved for Reſtaur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of our Gracious Sovereign which happy day now haſtening, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like the wings of morning makin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haſte to a perfect day, <hi>Hugh Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with that black crew, deſire to be a abſcond, and as much in the dark <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their actions had been, now play <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inventus.</hi> But the eye of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty Providence, at laſt found him out Although he flew for ſanctuary to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Womans bed, that had now newl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lyen in. But the intelligence bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> certain, that he was there they preſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in upon him, he denying his name t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be <hi>Peters,</hi> but his name was <hi>Thompſon</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:50469:30"/> and begging of the Conſtable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e reſt, that they would not call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im <hi>Peters,</hi> for fear the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould tear him to pieces: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g brought to the Tower, he not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nely confeſſed himſelf to Sir <hi>John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>binſon,</hi> but was well known to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſame man.</p>
            <p>And here we ſhall conclude his wicked life, and come to the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his miſerable death. Being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yal, it is ſtrange to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hink with what ſtupidity he beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed himſelf; for although upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Arraignment he ſaid he would not plead guilty for all the World, yet upon his Tryal he was found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be as is before expreſt, one of the principal Actors in that ſad Tragedy, and brought in guilty by his Jury, not being able to plead the leaſt rational circumſtance for himſelf.</p>
            <p>On Tueſday following, he was ordered to die, but was much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50469:31"/> both in ſpirit and mind, for he retained much of his former Frenetick humours now he was going to Execution: He was drawn upon a Hurdle from New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate to <hi>Charing Croſs,</hi> ſitting therein like a Sot all the way he went, and either plucking the Straws therein, or gnawing the Fingers of his Gloves. Being come to the place aforeſaid, not like a Miniſter, but like ſome ignorant Atheiſt, he aſcended the Ladder, but knew not what to ſay or how to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the hour of his death, but ſtanding there a while, at length he perfectly burſt forth into wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and then after a little pauſe he held his hand before his eyes, he prayed for a ſhort ſpace, and now the Hangman being ready, he very often remembred him to make haſte by checking him with the Rope, and at laſt very unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly he turned him off the Lader,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50469:31"/> and after he had hung almoſt a quarter of an hour, he was cut down and quartered: His Head was ſet on <hi>London</hi> Bridge, and his Limbs on the City Gates.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> written by an ingenuous Spectator of his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>See here the laſt and beſt <hi>Edition,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Hugh,</hi> the Author of <hi>Sedition;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So full of <hi>Errors,</hi> 'tis not fit</l>
               <l>To read, till <hi>Dun</hi>'s Corrected it:</l>
               <l>But now 'tis perfect, nay far more,</l>
               <l>'Tis better <hi>bound</hi> then 'twas before.</l>
               <l>And now I hope it is no ſin</l>
               <l>To ſay, <hi>Rebellion,</hi> take thy ſwing:</l>
               <l>For he that ſayes, ſayes much amiſs</l>
               <l>That <hi>Hugh</hi> an <hi>Independent</hi> is.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:50469:32"/>
            <head>The Life of Mr. THOMAS SCOT.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Thomas S ot</hi> was born in the County of <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham,</hi> of no noted Family: The firſt occaſion of their publick notice, was by the wicked projects of this unfortunate m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, He was ſent to <hi>London</hi> by his friends to be brought up in ſome honeſt Calling, which he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo honeſt as to practice. The higheſt preferment that he could reach before the Wars, was being a Partner to a Brewer in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct of <hi>Bridewel,</hi> but of his honeſty and faithfulneſs in his carriage
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50469:32"/> therein, I leave to his acquaintance and Neighbours to judge.</p>
            <p>But he hoping to make better profit by having a hand in brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of State Affairs, makes friends to a Borough in <hi>Buckinghamſhire,</hi> where he was choſen a Burgeſs, and ſo improves the good will of this his Country, who made him a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament man, to the deſtruction and confuſion of the whole; for being pre-prejudiced againſt the B ſhops and a conſtant envier a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Monarchy, he now had an opportunity to vent his malice, and ſpit his venome by long Speeches and dilated Harr a gues in the Parliament.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Tho. Scot</hi> being now crept into the Houſe of Commons, whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Treaſon into many of the Members ears, animating the War, and ripping up and ſtudying aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations thereunto, was forward up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Tumultuous occaſions, to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50469:33"/> exaſperate the people againſt the Biſhops, and through them, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at the King himſelf.</p>
            <p>But it is to be obſerved how the drift of his malice ſoon after ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared: This covetous wretch was ſo great an enemy to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, onely that he might be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of their Lands; for not long after that too forward Abolition of that Order and Government, he then gets into the Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburies</hi> houſe at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and there Lords it with as much ſtate, as if he wanted nothing but the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of an Arch Biſhop.</p>
            <p>And now his eſtate and his facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous principles encreaſe together, graſping as much of the Church Lands as he could, and being of opinion that it had been no Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, if he had pulled down the Churches themſelves; and did not think it enough for himſelf to be engaged in the Lands of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50469:33"/> Church, but he would engage his Son in the Lands of the King, who was choſen, and acted as one of the Truſtees at <hi>Worceſter</hi> houſe in the <hi>Strand,</hi> for ſale of the Lands of the King, Queen and Prince.</p>
            <p>In the year 1647. finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo far precipitated in the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and promoting of the War, he ſticks cloſe to the Army, and ſayes, There was no putting up the Sword after they had once drawn it againſt the King, is admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the conſultations of their private Meetings: When they were contriving the death of the King, he was one of the cheif un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminers of that Parliament; For when they Voted, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of the King at the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> were a ſufficient ground for the peace of the Nations, he with others, and their never failng Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, flie to the Army, and coming to Town cauſed moſt of them to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50469:34"/> be ſecluded; and he was one of the forty Members that Uſurped the Title of a Parliament after they had driven away almoſt three hundred of their number, and was a chief inſtrument in ſetting on foot that wicked thing called <hi>An Act of Parliament for the Trying of the King.</hi> And becauſe the Kings Seal could not be uſed to paſs an Act againſt himſelf, they all ſet their own Seals to that horrid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, amongſt whom, this Mr. <hi>Scot</hi>'s was one.</p>
            <p>Every day that this wretched Crew (called the High Court of Juſtice) ſate, this Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> would be ſure to be amongſt them; he was preſent and ſtood up when that impudent and unparaleld Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident commanded the Sentence to be read, and he ſet his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nd and Seal to that bloody Warrant for the Execution.</p>
            <p>And now they thought their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50469:34"/> work was done after they had thus barbarouſly murthered the King: Thoſe few Members take upon them the Authority of the three Nations, and Mr. <hi>Sc t</hi> is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of their Council of State, acts in the nature of a Secretary of State, and is made the onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to mannage the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntelligence, as well Forraign as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omeſtick, both publick and private, and thinks himſelf little other then a petty Prince, in which condition he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till the year 1653. at which time they were diſſolved by the Ambition of the Grand Uſurper.</p>
            <p>He kept under him (during the time of his domination) ſeveral Spies, called Purſivants, and was a continual perplexer of <hi>Printers</hi> and <hi>Bookſellers,</hi> not ſuffering them to vent the leaſt light of Tranſactions fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the information of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople, but by his Subſtitutes, eſpecially <hi>Ledſum;</hi> all honeſt and true Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50469:35"/> was not onely ſeized and ſuppreſſed, but the Divulgers thereof were both puniſhed and impriſoned.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> took the Government upon himſelf, this buſie body lay idle all the time, onely behaved himſelf like a Waſp upon all occaſions putting forth his ſting: He did nothing obſervable during that Uſurpation worth our mention in this abridgement of their actions.</p>
            <p>But that Government under him ceaſing, and <hi>Richard Cromwel</hi> now being ſetled in the ſcornful ſeat of his Father, Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> begins again to ſhew himſelf, and was a very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive inſtrument in dethroning that fooliſh pretender, and a chief Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor at <hi>Wallingford</hi> houſe with <hi>Lambert, Fleetwood, &amp;c.</hi> for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing of the Rump Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Which ſucceeding according to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50469:35"/> his deſire, he now appears as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent as before, and is re-inſtated in the places which under the Rump Parliament he had formerly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</p>
            <p>But a ſecond breach occaſioned their ſecond diſturbance, <hi>Lambert</hi> having lately victoriouſly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an undiſciplined handful of men in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir <hi>George Booth,</hi> comes up to <hi>London</hi> like a Conqueror, and ſets the Wheels ſo on work, as if poſſible, to turn out that Rump Parliament again, and ſo by <hi>Olivers</hi> policy to take the Government up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf. And thus theſe Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors fell out amongſt themſelves, which brought Our Soveraign to his Right.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> was much tickled at this ſudden News, and appears now as one that could not brook ſuch an in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rruption; to which purpoſe, he with Mr. <hi>Weaver,</hi> Sir <hi>Anthony
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50469:36"/> Aſhley Cooper, &amp;c.</hi> Gentlemen of far honeſter principles then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſet on foot ſeveral deſigns for regaining the ſitting of that Juncto, as that of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> taking the Tower of <hi>London, &amp;c.</hi> which brought them again once more to their Uſurped Government, and he is imployed by them, with Mr. <hi>Luke Robinſon,</hi> to be as Spies over the actions and intentions of wiſe General <hi>Monck,</hi> who was now upon his March towards <hi>London,</hi> which proved ineffectual for their deſigne; for although they would not ſuffer him to ſpeak with any perſons but where they were pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent, yet they could not gain from him the leaſt cranny to peep out at whereby they might underſtand or gueſs at his future intended pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
            <p>Soon after, that Noble General gives the Secluded Members liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to go into the Houſe, who till
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50469:36"/> that time had been debarred by force from that their priviledge, who onely ſate to conſider how another Parliament might be called and to diſſolve that but ſuppoſed Parliament: And before their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended diſſolution Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> ſtands up and moves the Houſe, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they did diſſolve, they would declare, That all the Proceedings which had been made in relation to the Kings murther, ſhould be confirmed by the Parliament; which motion was ſo ill recented, that had not ſome moderate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons interceeded, he had been at that time called to the Bar of the Houſe, for mentioning them to be ſo barbarous as to be conceived to countenance or own the Kings murther; at which time he uſed this wicked expreſſion, That he deſired no greater honour then to have it Engraved upon his Tomb-ſtone, <hi>Here lies Tho, Scot,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:50469:37"/> one of the Judges of the late King, to the end the World might take notice of it.</p>
            <p>The Parliament which met the 23d. of <hi>April,</hi> being ſummoned, Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> flies beyond the Seas, to ſeek a place for that hot head, which he ſaid he could not hide, which proved true, for not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Majeſties reſtauration, he was taken notice of in <hi>Fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ders,</hi> and there ſeized and ſent Priſoner into <hi>England,</hi> and brought to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſome time until he was brought to his Tryal.</p>
            <p>Upon his Arraignment in the <hi>Old Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ley</hi> he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d little to ſay for himſelf, pleading the power by, which he acted to be a legal p wer bec uſe they were owned by the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But being told that the power by which he acted were not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enth part of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England,</hi> and that if there
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50469:37"/> had been a ful Houſe of Commons, and Lords likewiſe, they could not by any Act of theirs take away the life of the pooreſt Cripple at the Gate, much leſs the Kings: He was left to his <hi>Jury,</hi> and ſo was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently found Guilty.</p>
            <p>And on Wedneſday following, he with others, were drawn from Newgate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a Hurdle to their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid appointed place of Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. All the way as he went, his countenance was compoſed with a ſeeming cheerful gravity, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to <hi>Charing Croſs</hi> he obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and inſenſibly aſcended the Ladder: He ſpake very little to the people, his chief buſineſs there, as he ſaid, being to pray which being ended, he made no long ſtay, but was ſoon executed and q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>artered, according to his Sentence; his Head was ſet up on the Gate of <hi>London</hi> Bridge, and his Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rters were ſet on the Gates of the City.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:50469:38"/>
               <l>This treacherous <hi>Scot</hi> deſired to have,</l>
               <l>No other <hi>Motto</hi> on his Grave.</l>
               <l>Then this; That he was one that laid</l>
               <l>This bloody Scene, anth' King betrayd.</l>
               <l>But he no Grave could now attain,</l>
               <l>Where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y that <hi>Motto</hi> ſhould remain.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:50469:38"/>
            <head>The Life of Col. Daniel Axtel.</head>
            <p>COl. <hi>Daniel Axtel</hi> was a man of a malicious and covetous ſpirit; he was born of very pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Parents, and ſent up to <hi>London</hi> to be put forth Apprentice: He had not ſtaid long at his Trade, which was a <hi>Grocer,</hi> before theſe deſtructed Nations began to ſhew their diſtempers; and ſeeing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but letting of it blood would (as they ſaid) procure its ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he appeared a very forward inſtrument in taking up of Armes: He went forth into the War but a private Souldier, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50469:39"/> being a ſpiritually gifted man (for ſo he was termed) he very quickly arrived at the mark of a more publick notice.</p>
            <p>When the Army were gathered together at <hi>New Market</hi> in a muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous manner againſt their Maſters the Parliament, Agitators were choſen out of each Company to repreſent their pretended grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Here Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> (then but an ordinary Officer) was looked upon as an eminent and fit perſon to carry on that factious and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed deſign of refuſing to disband the Army, when they were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereunto by the Parliament, and when the Parliament and the King had come to Tearms of Peace in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> he comes up in the head of the Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and at the Bar of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſe, he is forward in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching the Members thereof, calling them rotten Members, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:50469:39"/> and at that time being Lieutenant Colonel to Col. <hi>Hewſons</hi> Regiment of Foot, he was very active that day the Secluded Members were impriſoned and diſturbed, and was more then ordinary Officious in the doing thereof.</p>
            <p>When the High Court of cruel Injuſtice was eſtabliſhed, all the time during their ſitting, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Guards in <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi> which attended them, and when the King came through the Hall to his Tryal, he commanded the Souldiers to cry Juſtice, Juſtice, and had the valour to beat ſuch as did not execute his commands; and when <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> taxed the King with delayes and trifling away time, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commons of <hi>England</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to anſwer to his Charge, (a Lady from the Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſaid not half the Commons of <hi>England</hi>) this Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> ſaid to s Souldiers, ſhoot the Whore,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50469:40"/> pull her down, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And after up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the laſt day of their ſitting, he again commanded them to cry Execution, Execution.</p>
            <p>Afterwards being the day when this unparaleld murther was to be accompliſhed, Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> was very buſie that morning at <hi>Cromwels</hi> Chamber door, where <hi>Ireton</hi> and <hi>Harriſon</hi> then lay together in <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> and Col. <hi>Hunks,</hi> Col. <hi>Hacker,</hi> and Col. <hi>Phaire,</hi> to whom the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xecution was directed, being ſent for thither, <hi>Oliver Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> would have had them ſigned a Sub warrant to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xecutioner for the murther of the King, but Col. <hi>Huncks</hi> refuſing, this Col. <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel</hi> told him, he was a peeviſh man, and that he was ſorry to think, that now they were going into a ſafe Harbour, Col. <hi>Huncks</hi> ſhould ſtrike Sail before they had caſt Anchor.</p>
            <p>He went afterwards into the next expedition for <hi>Ireland,</hi> where
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:50469:40"/> he ſoon comenced Colonel. And it is ſtrange what Helliſh cruelties he uſed there, not onely againſt the Native <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whom he would mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like Vermine but even againſt Proteſtants and <hi>Engliſh</hi> not favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring either, although he had not onely promiſed but aſſured them fair Quarter.</p>
            <p>The Army at this time being univerſally Anabaptiſts, and under the Government of that Grand en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them <hi>Henry Ireton,</hi> then Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Son in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw to <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> this Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> was ſo too, being a general diſowner of Orthodox Miniſters, and a great countenancer of Sects and Factions, and a ſelf conceited Preacher him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>He was made Governour of the County and City of <hi>Kilkenny</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and here he ſhews his cruelty ſo conſpicuous, as that his very mercileſs brethren of the Army
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50469:41"/> condemn him: He hanged what Gentry of the Country he pleaſed, whether they were guilty or not, never affording them any Tryal, but making his own Will his Law, he exerciſed it according to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, by reaſon whereof, many Innocents cauſeleſly ſuffered; and for which, his own brethren on the Army drew up Articles againſt him in a Court Marſhal, and he had then received puniſhment for the price of blood, had not the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt, and <hi>Charls Fleetwood</hi> in the head of them, at that time being the predominant party, paſt by the buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Soon after <hi>Charles Fleetwood</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing removed from the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Henry Cromwel</hi> ſent over thither to repreſent the Lord Deputy of that Nation; the Anabaptiſts was not only diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced by him, but their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation was reduced and levelled
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:50469:41"/> equal to thoſe of different prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> perceiving (as likwiſe that now they were not ſuffered to have that rambling lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to domineer over the weak brethren as formerly, for ſuch they counted all not alike principled with themſelves) he with three others, formerly like himſelf, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning <hi>Charles Fleetwood,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they pleaſed, <hi>viz.</hi> Col. <hi>Barrow Adjutant,</hi> General <hi>Allen,</hi> and Quarter Maſter Gen. <hi>Vernon,</hi> came to <hi>Henry Cromwel,</hi> and in a great deal of ſeeming diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, delivered him up their Commiſſions, from that time ceaſing to act any further, becauſe they could not act as they pleaſed.</p>
            <p>There was very little more obſervable during <hi>Oliver Cromwels</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ife, onely that in that vacancy he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad a fair opportunity to encreaſe his eſtate, which indeed he made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſe to at leaſt 2000 lib. <hi>per annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:50469:42"/>
            <p>At laſt <hi>Oliver</hi> dies, and <hi>Richards</hi> weakneſs being practiſed upon, (by his cunning and treacherous Kindred, though falſe friends) Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> appears very buſie therein, and the Rump Parliament appearing again upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> he has order for a Regiment of Foot, and is ſent to <hi>Ireland,</hi> where he had not been long, before Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> appeared in the head of a party in <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> for the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming whereof when the Army of <hi>England</hi> were thought too little but help muſt he had from <hi>Ireland</hi> alſo, for which purpoſe Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> is ſent over ommander in Cheif of the Foot, and Col. <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>key</hi> of the Horſe, which coming over of theirs proved ineffectual, for that the buſineſs was done before their landing.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Lambert</hi> and the Rump Parliament fell out, Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> is very forward and aſſiſtant for the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:50469:42"/> diſſolving of them; he is one of the Saints at <hi>Wallingford</hi> houſe, and a contriver of the ſettlement of the Nation by a Committee of Safety, and he likewiſe is reſolved with <hi>Lambert</hi> And the reſt to fetch Gen. <hi>Monck</hi> out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or to make him ſubmit to their tearms; and accordingly he went down to head the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Brigade, then in <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhire,</hi> and marches them into the <hi>North,</hi> but they very unwilling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took that buſineſs, and although with entreaties, beggings, prayers, and tears he wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d them to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceed in th Good Old Cauſe yet he coul not prevail upon them; for they diſcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed both <hi>Lambert</hi> and their own cheif Officers, and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare for General <hi>Monck</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Parliament, and now Col <hi>Ax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el</hi> is left to ſeek his fortune, which at that time was more deſpera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> when he firſt left his Maſter to go into he Army.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:50469:43"/>
            <p>When the King ws comming home, he commits himſelf to the private Chamber of a particular friend, who thought it not ſafe to entertain him long, ſince Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was made or for that purpoſe, and ſo delivering him up to the next Conſtable he was ordered to be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter that, he was brought to his Tryal in te Old-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iley, where his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lea, was, That he had d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng during the time of the Tryal of the King, but what he was commanded t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by his ſuperiour Officers, That he might have ſuffered as much for diſobeying them, as now he was like to do for performing them; That he was no Parliament man, none of the High Court of Juſtice, no Counſellor, no Contriver, none that Sate, none that Signed to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings death, onely acted as a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier under command by virtue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50469:43"/> thereof. But the Witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the aforementioned paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges of his life, and that he had often confeſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that he had been a cheif inſtrument in bringing the King to that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tal Axe, as alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other black and horrid, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, to prove him a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple promoter thereof; he was ſoon found guilty by the Jury, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly received Sentence of condemnation.</p>
            <p>And on Friday following he was drawn from Newgate to Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn upon an Hurdle: He ſeemed to be penitent, but yet retained a cheerful countenance. Being come to the Gallowes, he ſeriouſly told the People, that he went out n the Wars at the beginning thereof, by the inſtigation and encouragement of a Miniſter in <hi>Ironmonger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ane,</hi> who ſtirred him with many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to ſhew him it was the cauſe of God <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and many words to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50469:44"/> the ſame effect. After which he prayed moſt affectionately for all ſorts of people, uttering many Heavenly and Chriſtian like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and at laſt concluding deſiring God for that poor Wretch that was then to imbrue his hands in his Blood, to bath his Soul in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt. His end Was full of penitence and ſorrow, and now being fitted to die, he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry willingly ſubmitted to the hand of Juſtice, and being hanged, was ſoon after quartered, and his Limbs are diſpoſed of upon the Gates of the City.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>This active Man commands the Guard</l>
               <l>Of that <hi>black</hi> Court, &amp; loud was heard</l>
               <l>To c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll for Juſtice, and did beat</l>
               <l>Such as would not the ſame repeat:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Friend,</hi> pray be patient, now I hope,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juſtice</hi> hath met you with a <hi>Rope.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:50469:44"/>
            <head>The Life of Gregory Clement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GReg. Clement</hi> was a man hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, worth the mention, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the wickedneſs of his lewd life; He was a Merchant by his firſt profeſsion, but failing therein and growing into a deſperate fortune, thought to thrive by merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing in Biſhops Lands, wherein he got a conſiderable eſtate: He was turned out of the Rump Parliam. for lying with his Maid at <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> but was received amongſt them again at their return after <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers</hi> interruption. His guilty Conſcience and his Ignorance toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, would not ſuffer him to make
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50469:45"/> any Plea at the Bar or Speech or Prayer at the Gallowes: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, he was asked whether he had any thing to ſay before the Hangman did his Office, he ſaid no, upon which, Execution was done, and being quartered, his Head was ſet upon <hi>London</hi> Bridge' and his Limbs diſpoſed of as the reſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:50469:45"/>
            <head>The Life of Col. Adrian Scroop.</head>
            <p>COl. <hi>Adrian Scroop</hi> was deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of a good Family in <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinghamſhire.</hi> He was in thoſe days a great Puritan and ſtickler againſt the Biſhops, which made him in the beginning of the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs to take up Armes againſt the King. He went forth at firſt a Captain of Horſe, but being inveterate againſt the King, he ſoon got preferment in the Army.</p>
            <p>He was no Parliament man, and yet was drawn in as he pretended, by <hi>Oliv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Cromwel</hi> to be one in the black Liſt for the Tryal of the King: He was moſt dayes at that Court when that wicked crew ſate
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50469:46"/> upon His <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jeſty,</hi> and eſpecially the laſt day w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. Sentence was giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, and afterwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſealed the bloody Warr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t for that horrid murther.</p>
            <p>I finde little mention of him all that ſhort time of <hi>Olivers</hi> Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But when the King came home, and ſet forth the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation commanding thoſe that were his Fathers Judges to appear, who were either fled or had hid themſelves; Col. <hi>Scroop</hi> comes in, and delivers himſelf up unto the Speaker, with ſome others, and they had made a Vote, that he ſhould be onely fined a years value of his eſtate: But ſoon after, he diſcourſing with General <hi>Brown</hi> about the Kings murther, juſtifies the act thereof, ſaying, <hi>He did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it to be no murther;</hi> with other expreſſions tending to prove that the King did deſerve death; which being reported to the Parliament,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50469:46"/> he was wholly excepted out of the Act of general pardon.</p>
            <p>And being brought to his Tryal in the <hi>Old Bailey,</hi> the chief part of his plea was not ſo much to juſtifie the act, as the power by which he acted, ſaying, That they were owned both at home and abroad, and that he was no Parliament man, but acted by their Authority, who were then the Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nations, and he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that Authority would excuſe him. But being told as all the reſt had been, the vanity of that plea, and the weakneſs of his Argument to prove the ſame, and how far they were from the leaſt colour of Authority, he was left to his Jury, who ſoon brought him in guilty: And on Wedneſday following, he was brought from Newgate to <hi>Charing Croſs</hi> upon a Hurdle. He ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to look very cheerfully upon the Ladder. He bewailed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50469:47"/> his unfortunate diſcourſe with General <hi>Brown</hi> to be the chief cauſe of his being brought thither. And after he had prayed a pretty ſpace, he ſurrendered himſelf up to death, which was ſoon done, and he was likewiſe quartered as the reſt before him had been, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of accordingly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:50469:47"/>
            <head>The Life of Mr Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arew.</head>
            <p>MR <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn Carew</hi> was bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cornw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and deſcended of a very ancient Family there: He was alwayes of very f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent principles; at laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rived at the ſame pitch of Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> with Major General <hi>Har iſon,</hi> and did pertake of the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with him; and it is no wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was one of the Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> King, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ng to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of his own Brother.</p>
            <p>All the time of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed very maliciouſly againſt the King, and indeed all kind of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50469:48"/> Monarchy. And when the Army came up to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge the Houſe, when indeed none wanted more purging then thoſe who were left after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in it. This Mr. <hi>Carew</hi> was one, and was very buſie at the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Act for eſtabliſhing a High Court of Juſtice; he ſet his Hand and Seal thereunto; he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s every day at the Court, and ſhewed his aſſent to the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> murther by ſtanding up when the Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence was read againſt him, and he likewiſe ſigned and Sealed to that w cked Warrant.</p>
            <p>Afterwards when the Rump Parliament was turned out, he Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred himſelf from any publick imployment, and kept himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and retired; being utterly ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſt <hi>Olivers</hi> Uſurpation, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he was againſt all M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>narchial G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vernment; and to give h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m his due, he was one that made the leaſt advantage by the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeries of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:50469:48"/> the times, then any man beſides which I knew in that Rump Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But the King being now come home, and he being known in his own Countrey to have been a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward inſtrument in that evil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, was ſeized there, and ſent up Priſoner to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and afterwards was brought to his Tryal with the reſt in the <hi>Old Baily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the reading of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which ſaid, that they had committed that horrid murther, not having the fear of God before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eyes, but being led by the inſtigation of the Devil; he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded error to the Inditement, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That what was done, was not in ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a fear, but in the fear of the moſt Holy and moſt Righteous Lord, which troubled the Court much, to ſee him make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od the Au hour of their murther. He was l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kewiſe about to have juſtified the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:50469:49"/> Authority of the Rump Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, called by Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> very well the Unparliamentary Juncto, which was anſwered as before, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other matter to plead for himſelf, the Jury went forth and found him guilty.</p>
            <p>And on Monday following, he was drawn from Newgate to <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Croſs</hi> on a Hurdle: Firſt having prepared himſelf by drinking three pintes of Sack to bear up his ſpirits, which cauſed a more then ordinary fluſhing in his face, all the way he went, and ſweat ſo much, that his Handkerchief could fearcely keep the water from running down his face: But his Spirits notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thus encouraged, could not out-dare the conflict. Being come to the Ladder, he lifted up his Hands and his Eyes, and had ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me private jaculations to himſelf. He ſpake very little, having now, as he ſaid little elſe to do then to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:50469:49"/> pray, in which he was but ſhort; wherein he deſired God to guide and direct the Kings Majeſty, to bleſs the three Nations with peace and happineſs, and all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therein; after which he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and being turned off the Ladder, he was ſoon dead, and quartered; which being done, his Quarters were begged by his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the King, and by him they are buried.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:50469:50"/>
               <l>This wretched and unhappy man</l>
               <l>Appears, and does the moſt he can</l>
               <l>To ſhed his Soveraigns Royal blood;</l>
               <l>Which done, cauſed another flood</l>
               <l>Of tears and ſorrow from all theſe</l>
               <l>Who with their <hi>Treaſon</hi> could not cloſe</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:50469:50"/>
            <head>The Life of Col. Francis Hacker.</head>
            <p>COl. <hi>Francis Hacker</hi> at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Wars was a man of a deſperate Fortune, one of a greater bulk of body then of perfections of mind; his factious principles advanced him in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and made him of great repute with thoſe Miſcreants who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived the Kings death, inſomuch, as the High Court of Injuſtice thought they could not pitch on a fitter man unto whom to direct that wicked Warrant for to ſee the Kings murther performed.</p>
            <p>That morning this horrible act
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:50469:51"/> was to be committed, <hi>Cromwel</hi> ſends for this <hi>Hacker,</hi> with Col. <hi>Phaire</hi> and Col. <hi>Huncks,</hi> and would have thoſe three to ſign a Sub War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for the Kings murther; the laſt two refuſed, but Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> ſubſcribes to whatſoever <hi>Cromwel</hi> himſelf had Written for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>This Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> likewiſe by virtue of the ſaid unwarrantable Warrant from that High Court of Injuſtice, goes to Col. <hi>Thomlinſon,</hi> who had then the cuſtody of the Kings perſon, and demands the King from him; carries him in the middeſt of his own Regiment through St. <hi>James Park,</hi> conducts him through the Gallery to the Banqueting Houſe, and from thence brings him upon the Scaffold; and there ſtands according to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Warrant, to ſee that bloody and unparaleld Execution.</p>
            <p>Afterwards he continues in the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:50469:51"/> Army, ſides with all parties that have the Government, and was a Col. in the Army at the very time when the King came home, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeized and examined in order to find out the myſtery of this Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, he vvas ſent to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and ſhortly after vvith the reſt brought to his Tryal.</p>
            <p>His Tryal vvas very ſhort, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he could not deny the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid actions of his in that unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raleld buſineſs; and being asked by the Court, <hi>to whom he directed his Sub warrant to ſtrike the fatal blow,</hi> he anſwered, <hi>that he did not know, for</hi> Cromwel, <hi>bid him write ſomthing and bid him put his hand to it, but whoſe hand he put in for that purpoſe he could not tell:</hi> This being all his plea, he was ſoon brought in guilty likewiſe.</p>
            <p>And on Friday following, he vvas drawn from <hi>Newgate</hi> on a Hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to <hi>Tyburn;</hi> vvhere he ſpake ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:50469:52"/> little for himſelf, onely left the vvhole buſineſs of prayer to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by Col. <hi>Axtel,</hi> vvho perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it for them both; after vvhich being ended, he vvas onely hanged, and being cut down he vvas put in a He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe vvhich was there brought to carry b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck his Body, his Son hath begged the ſame from the King, vvho granted him his Fathers body vvithout quartering, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buried the ſame in the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:50469:52"/>
            <p>As for Quarter Maſter <hi>William Hewle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in regard that though he be Condemned, yet is Reprieved, in order to a clear diſcovery of this wicked act: I ſhall leave his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and Deſcription to the time, when Juſtice ſhall likewiſe make him an Example for putting on a Vizor on his Faces and a Frock on his Body for ſuch a horrid purpoſe.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:50469:53"/>
            <p>There are eighteen more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Hard eſs Waller, William He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venningham, Iſaac Pennington, Hen. Ma tin, Gilbert Millington, Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ert Titch urn, Owen Roe, Robert Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Smith, Edmund Harvey, John Dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Vincent Potter, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>land, George Fleetwood Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yne, Thomas W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, James T mple, Peter Temple;</hi> of whom I think n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t convenient to write <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g of their lives, til I ſhall be prepared to give an account al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o of the manner of their deaths. Theſe are cloſe priſoners in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> till the pleaſure of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhall be declared concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:50469:53"/>
            <p>Several others there are, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Say, John Barkstead,</hi> Sir <hi>Michael Liveſly Miles Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, Thomas Woogan,</hi> Mr. <hi>Love, Daniel Blagrave, Andrew Broughton, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ward Denby, John Dixwel, Thomas Challo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, John L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſle, William Cawley, John Okey, Will. Goff, John Hewſon, Valentine Wanton, Ed Whaley, Edw. Ludlow, Cor. Holland;</hi> Who vvander about the World as Vagabons, like <hi>Cain</hi> vvith they cry of blood at their Heels, vvho at laſt vvill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o queſtion be found out by the All ſearching hand of divine Juſtice, and brought to receive a condigne puniſhment f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Treaſon; of whom alſo in time we ſhall give you a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect account.</p>
            <p>And thus I conclude the ſtory of theſe few wretched and miſerable Traytors, whoſe Limbs are ſet up as <hi>Lots</hi> Wife's Pillar of Salt, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:50469:54"/> examples of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties juſt puniſhment, that thus would imbrew their hands in the Sacred blood of his own Anointed, which was ſo far a Deicide, as Kings are called Gods upon the Earth, and which ought to be the prayers of all truly Chriſtianized, That God would cleanſe the City and Nation from the guilt of that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood, ſo inhumanely and unchriſtianly ſhed, as before ſail, and keep theſe Nations from Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and privy Conſpiracy, from all falſe Doctrine and Hereſie, that no Jeſuitical plots from abroad, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtical or Schiſmatical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations at home may he ever able to raiſe Sedition in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the peace of the King.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:50469:54"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>Henry Ireton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>HEnry Ireton,</hi> Son-in-Law to <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> a man full of wicked policy and contrivance; and his Fathers chief Councellour, and ſecond in all his undertakings: he arives at <hi>Comiſary</hi> Gene. in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> very factious in his Principles, and a great encourager of all that were ſuch; A great Promoter of the <hi>Kings</hi> Death, &amp; one that ſtood in the margent of <hi>Olivers</hi> enterprize in that wicked murder; he was not only of the High Court of Juſtice, but took upon him with Major Gen. <hi>Hariſon,</hi> &amp;c. the appointing of the time, place, and manner of the <hi>Kings</hi> Execution.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:50469:55"/>
            <p>After which he goes over with his Father <hi>Cromwell</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and by him is left Lord Deputy thereof; here he made victorious in the redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of many Gariſons there, and at laſt ſets down before <hi>Limerick,</hi> which Siege was the laſt that ever he made, for not long after the ſurrender of that City, he dyed of the Plague, his Death was very ſuddain and ſtrange to the Army; but however he was ſent into <hi>England,</hi> carryed to <hi>Summerſet</hi> Houſe where his Father mocks his Body with that vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which himſelf had often declared againſt, and a Funeral in great ſtate is made by the Army, interring him among the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Iretons</hi> Wife <hi>Oliver Cromwels</hi> own Daughters ordered by her Fathers means 2000 pound in money, and 2000 pound <hi>per Annum</hi> out of the Land of <hi>Goran</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> being of the Lands belonging to the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> which he hath now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50469:55"/> again according to an Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> made in that behalf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oliver</hi> erects a Tomb for this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Sectarian Champion, with his Effigies, and his Wifes lying by him in King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſevenths Chappel, which is ſince ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly broken down, and no foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtep leſt of his remembrance in that royal and ſtately memorial of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings, and his name is now as rotten, as his Carcaſs periſhed through the wickedneſs of his bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:50469:56"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>John Bradſhaw.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>JOhn Bradſhaw</hi> borne in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> (and better ſure it had been if he had nere been born) a man, although brought up in that honourable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Law, yet a ſhameful and moſt wicked deſtroyer of the very foundation and corner ſtone there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was made Judge of the County Palatine of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and afterwards of the Sheriffes Court in <hi>Guild-hall London,</hi> and from thence moſt auda, tiouſly and impudently he appears in the Front of the High Court of Juſtice, as their Preſident; and judges him that was the Judge of the Law: and now I even tremble to think how I ſaw him the day of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50469:56"/> Kings Tryal in Scarlet, with a heart and conſcience as deep dyed as his Gown, moſt diviliſhly &amp; inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtaining that white innocency of the Kings Majeſty, with approbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and wicked language, which I dare not mention in this place, unleſs I give occaſion of making that ſad wound to bleed afreſh in the ſight of all tender, and truly pious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <p>This wicked and unparralleld murder, was not called to account in his Life but he lives (though in a very timerous condition) and acts as Preſident to the Councel of State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, and hath given him (by thoſe who thought that by taking of Gods anointed, they did the Devil good ſervice) ſeveral conſiderable Revenues, both in <hi>Hampſhire</hi> and <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> and among the reſt lives (though not ſecurely) in the Deana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where for his ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake he built his Study on the top
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50469:57"/> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Abbey, higer than the like was ever ſeen before, getting as nigh Heaven as he could whilſt he lived, as not expecting to come there when he dyed.</p>
            <p>All the time of <hi>Olivers</hi> ſhort Reign, he acted not: But the Rump <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> coming into play again, he is again reinſtated in his former Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentſhip, and is made the prime Lord Comiſſioner of the great Seal of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Lambert</hi> turned out the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen again, he raves now like one ſtark mad, flinging out of the room in uſury, and calling them all Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and whilſt the <hi>Committee</hi> of Safety ſate, he ſeeing now that all things would make for the Kings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, goes home &amp; takes his Bed, &amp; never comes abroad more, his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed body was tortured wiih many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, languiſhing in much pain and miſery, inſomuch that he was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reported, and really thought to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50469:57"/> be dead before he truly was, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience being ſeared, he repented not of his aforeſaid wicked practiſes; and at laſt this miſerable man paſſed through the aforeſaid, much afflicted and tormented body to the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Judgment of God, and no doubt is gone to his place, his body was burned in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Abbey.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:50469:58"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>Doctor Doriſlavs.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>DOctor Doriſlavs</hi> formerly a Doctor of the civil (by him made the uncivill) Law was by an order of this corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted piece of the Parliament, made one of the chief Councel with Mr. <hi>Ask</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cooke,</hi> to contrive and prepare a charge againſt the King, and very confidently he appears in the Court againſt him, ſeconding Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> in his wicked demanding of Juſtice againſt the King. This Dr. <hi>Doriſlavs</hi> pleaded that the King ought to anſwer the Court, and not in the leaſt to queſtion their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which proved his own death at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt; for not long after, he being ſent
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50469:58"/> into <hi>Holland</hi> in the nature of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent from the Parliament, was ſtob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in his lodging in the <hi>Hague</hi> by ſome reſolute perſons, who likewiſe not queſtioning their own authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) reſolved to make him a part ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Kings Murder, his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was brought from <hi>Holland</hi> to <hi>Baynards</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Thames</hi> Street, &amp; from thence privately interred &amp; accompanied with ſome pretended mourners in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Abbey.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:50469:59"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>Thomas Hammond.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THOmas Hammond</hi> of <hi>Surry,</hi> and of no great fortune there. He went out into the Army one of the Life guard of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and was afterwards made Lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Gen. to the traine of Artillery under the Lord <hi>Fairfax;</hi> this Col <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> afterwards was preferred to have the cuſtody of the King at the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> and there not only undutifully but very ſawcily and peremptorily behaved himſelf to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, not ſuffering the King to have any papers about him but what he would firſt peruſe; and when the Parliament made thoſe Votes of non addreſſes; as it hath been credibly reported, Letters were
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50469:59"/> write to this Col. <hi>Hammond,</hi> by <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> (who found that nothing could be done in their own affaire, till the King were taken off) that he ſhould either remove the King out of the way or priſon him by one means or other. Upon which Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi> then being in the Country, writs a letter to the Houſe, that Major <hi>Rolfe</hi> had confeſt that ſuch a Letter was written to <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> to the aforeſaid purpoſe: but that <hi>Hammond</hi> had a good allowance for keeping the King, and therefore would not do it becauſe he would not looſe his allowance, and deſired the ſaid Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi> to joyn with him in conveighing the King to ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate place, and then they would do with him what they pleaſed.</p>
            <p>This buſineſs was ſtrangely hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up in the Houſe, the Army party therein arguing that <hi>Osborn</hi> was a Malignant, and no notice was fit to be taken of his words; others
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50469:60"/> ſaid that the Examination of the buſineſs was a Malignant deſign to draw Col. <hi>Hammond</hi> to this Town that ſo the King might make his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape in the <hi>Cols.</hi> abſence. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the buſineſs was then huſht up, yet Mr. <hi>Osborne</hi> and others of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to confirme the deſign, and that <hi>Rolfe</hi> was appointed to piſtol the King, but ſtill they endeaver to abſcond the truth, <hi>Rolfe</hi> is ſent up by Col. <hi>Hammond</hi> with letters to the Houſe, and therein denies the buſineſs, and although the thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared plain, (notwithſtanding <hi>Rolfe</hi> with a trembling voice not halfe loud enough to make a ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory anſwer, pleads at the Houſe Bar, that there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s no ſuch thing) he was ſuddainly conveyed out of the way by the Army, &amp; <hi>Hammond</hi> was never ſo much as queſtioned.</p>
            <p>Preſently after the deſign being carried on for the Kings Murther this Col. <hi>Hammond</hi> preſents to the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50469:60"/> Houſe a Scandalous libel called the Agreement of the people, which contained nothing elſe but a deſire of the Kings tryal and a ſubverſion of the ancient Laws of the Land, which was ordered to be printed, although not a hundred part of the people had not the leaſt thought thereof.</p>
            <p>And the next thing is the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King to his tryal in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter Hall</hi> inſtead of the pretended making him a glorious King, and bringing him home to his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and this Col. <hi>Hammond</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the advice, and to the great greife of Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>) appeared as one of the Kings Judges, and afterwards became one of the great promotets of the Tyrannical uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and in the year 1654. When <hi>Oliver</hi> took the Protectorſhip up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; Col. <hi>Hammond</hi> is ſent into <hi>Ireland</hi> as one of the Privy Counſel of that Nation, <hi>Charles Fleetwood</hi> was made Lord Deputy, and <hi>Milts
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50469:61"/> Corbet,</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l. <hi>Thom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon,</hi> &amp;c. were made of the ſame Councell w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> him, for <hi>Oliver</hi> durſt not truſt ſuch near him who had ſo lately betrayed the King; as conceiving they would do the like by him; but Col. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> being landed at <hi>Dublin</hi> his Councelſhip was ſoon ended.</p>
            <p>For before a fortnight was ended he dyed of a ſpotted Feaver there very ſuddenly and unexpectedly, dying ſenecleſs, and therefore no accompt can be given whether he repented of that horrid murther or no; <hi>Fleetwood</hi> and his factious crew, gave him a ſolemne funeral and interred his Body in <hi>Chriſt-Church Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I cannot but obſerve, how that politique uſurper <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> deſired to remove all thoſe who were in the leaſt concerned in the Kings death as farre from him as he could for the aforeſaid reaſons. Who were all ſent into <hi>Ireland, viz.</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50469:61"/> This
<list>
                  <item>C. <hi>Hammond,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>John Iones,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lievt Gen <hi>Ludlow,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>le,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Hewſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Phatre,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C. M. <hi>Thomlinſon</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Miles Corbet,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Juſtice Cooke,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Axtell H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wlet,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Huncks,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With many other private Officers, of the Army.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:50469:62"/>
            <head>The Life of Colonel <hi>Richard Deane.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>RIchard Deane</hi> was firſt brought up by a <hi>Hoyman</hi> belonging to the Town of <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards going to Sea, was Boatſwain of a ſhip. But the Warrs coming on, he goes forth into the Army, and there thrives in many ſucceſſive im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, becauſe a man of like principles with thoſe that then had the domination, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Sectarian</hi> (which was the greateſt) part of the Army when the Kings Death was contrived amongſt them: this Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Deane</hi> is a very forward buſie-body, to promote and countenance it; he was one of the High Court of Injuſtice, Seals the Warrant for the Murther, and with <hi>Hariſon</hi> and with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50469:62"/> 
               <hi>Ireton</hi> appoints the place of Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>After which he continued with the Army, went into <hi>Scotland</hi> with <hi>Cromwell</hi> when he conquered the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting Profeſſors where he was a Colonel of Horſe, and finally he is made one of the General at Sea with General <hi>Monck,</hi> and General <hi>Blake,</hi> in the Fights which were made with the <hi>Dutch;</hi> but in the ſecond Fight with them, he encouraging the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, was ſhot in pieces with a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Bullet, and all the ſmall remains they could find of him, were Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>find up and brought to <hi>Greenwich,</hi> and from thence were carryed by water in a ſolemn manner to <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and buried in the Chappel of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:50469:63"/>
            <head>The Life of Colonel <hi>Thomas Pride.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THo. Pride</hi> a man of a very mean (yet of a very uncertain) Birth, ſome of the Ancients have reported that he was a poor boy brought up by the Pariſh of St. <hi>Brides, Alies</hi> St. <hi>Bridgets London,</hi> and by them put forth at firſt, to an Ale-Houſe-keeper in <hi>Bride Lane</hi> to draw drink, but whether this be true or no I will not aſſert it: But the firſt mention that I find of him, was, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing a Servant to Mr. <hi>Hiccocks</hi> a Brewer in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and now living in the <hi>Bridg-houſe</hi> in S. <hi>Tulyes Street,</hi> there, with him he was a Drayman, and a common carrier of Beer with the Slings.</p>
            <p>When the Warrs began (he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50469:63"/> a buſling fellow in any diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance) he went forth an <hi>Enſigne</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> but by his continual ſiding with People like himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> Ignorant, yet impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in all their proceedings, he at laſt commences Colonel of a foot Company, &amp; now his meaneſs aims at nothing more than to be one of the Princes of the People.</p>
            <p>And when the Army at <hi>New-Market-Heath</hi> began the buſineſs of agitators, and by that means to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their old Maſters the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Colonel <hi>Pride</hi> encourages and animates them thereunto, and upon their coming to <hi>London,</hi> he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears a great ſtickler to have the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached Members, and Major Gen. <hi>Browne</hi> brought to Juſtice, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the greater part of the Houſe was ſo honeſt as to ſcorne to be taught and frighted into any illegal and baſe practiſes by the Army. This Colonel <hi>Pride</hi> together with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50469:64"/> Sir <hi>Hardreſs Walter,</hi> &amp; Col. <hi>Hewſon,</hi> ſeize all the aforeſaid honeſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Members, driving them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the exerciſe of their truſt comitted to their charge by their Country, and for ſome time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the greateſt part of them into an Ordinary, called <hi>Hell</hi> near <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall,</hi> which accaſioned ſome to uſe that expreſſion that <hi>Pride</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this he proceeds according as the faction lead him, and is a great Councellour in all the conſultations about the Kings Death, and when the King was brought from <hi>Windſor</hi> to his own Houſe at St. <hi>Jamſes.</hi> Col. <hi>Pride</hi> was very angry that the King was brought into his Chamber, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (it being then cold weather) it was only for a ſmall time (Col. <hi>Pride</hi> having a fire in that Chamber) until another fire in another room could be provided for the King.</p>
            <p>And now the time drawing near
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50469:64"/> wherein they intended this horrid Murther; Colonel <hi>Pride</hi> is made one of the Kings judges, he is among them very active every day, and when that black ſentence was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, Col. <hi>Pride</hi> ſets his hand &amp; ſeal to the murder, and with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment is upon the guard that day it was accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>Matters thus ſuceeding, and his Pockets being fil'd with the ſpoils of the people, he begins to think, then of his Draymans place, yet of a Brewers trade, and accordingly he laid out a conſiderable ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney upon a Brew-houſe in <hi>Pie-Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> and by his Wife and ſubſtitutes kept the ſame for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>After came on the Warrs of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which when <hi>Cromwel</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook, he is a chief follower of his ſaid Maſter, and is very forward in that enterpriz. And after when the <hi>Scotch Trophies</hi> and Colours wer
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50469:65"/> taken, and for the honour of that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory hanged up in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall;</hi> he was the Man that uttered the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, that he would have the <hi>Lawyers</hi> Gowns hang'd there too.</p>
            <p>And thus he continues till <hi>Oliver</hi> takes the Government upon himſelf, Col. <hi>Pride</hi> aſſiſts him in this too, and ſtands up very much for this new made <hi>Protector,</hi> noe wayes doubting but that if <hi>Oliver</hi> were a <hi>King</hi> he ſhould be one of his Inferior <hi>Princes;</hi> not long after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dubd him S. <hi>Thomas Pride,</hi> and yet by his uſurping Maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er when they were among themſelvs was often called Sir. <hi>Thomas Slings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> which indeed was the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name of the two.</p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Pride</hi> being of a very great corpulent Body, by reaſon whereof his Gate was very uncomely, <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> would uſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſay, when he ſaw him comming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owards him, ſee here how <hi>Pride</hi> comes wadling too and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as if he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the Slings upon his back.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:50469:65"/>
            <p>And being newly Knighted, he thought to adventure upon ſome noble Atchievement to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf famous, and his firſt encounter was at the Beare-Garden, where the Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es felt the couragousneſs of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> valour, and were all ſlain in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fight, upon which Col. <hi>Pride</hi> can off the Conquerer;</p>
            <p>For which and other ſervices, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> valourous Knight was ſuddenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter made a Lord, and thinks th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lords place would become a Dr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man very well; This mock hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſate not long before the Fabricator of it had an end put to his Life, and Col. <hi>Pride</hi> thought it not manners to ſtay behind him, whome he had alwayes followed in all his deſigns, and fearing a ſwing, inſteed of his ſlings, he dyed about a month after him, neer <hi>Nonſuch</hi> in the County of <hi>Surry,</hi> which <hi>Parke</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> ſo called, he had as his Portion for his aforeſaid wicked Services, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50469:66"/> of his Death is uncertain, as that of his Birth, being buried in a Church, near there abouts, in the County of <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:50469:66"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>Francis Allen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>FRancis Allen,</hi> a Citizen and Gold Smith of <hi>London,</hi> and Lived Over againſt St. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi> Church, neer <hi>Temple Bar,</hi> was a great ſtickler againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and one that had no way to improve his now decaying Eſtate, but by ſiding with the riſing Sectaries; by which means he was made one of the Commiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ners for their Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and a Truſtee for Sale of the Lands of the <hi>Biſhops, Deans,</hi> and <hi>Chapters.</hi> And the time coming on wherein his Soveraignes bloud was to be ſpilt, he appears a forward Deſigner of that wicked Act, and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:50469:67"/> accepts very readily of the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one of the Kings Judges; where he appeared every day to propagate the Murther, and was a great encourager of others to doe the ſame. He likewiſe Signed to the warrant for the Execution, and was ever after a continued Rump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and a great enemy of <hi>Olivers,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he diſſolved them: and I think it will not be unſeaſonable to inſert in this place part of a mock hymn, which was made pretended<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Mr. <hi>John Goodwin;</hi> although onely a Jeer made in imitation of the like <hi>Drollery</hi> which he made and cauſed to be Sung in his Church.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſpake one <hi>Allen</hi> of the City,</l>
               <l>at which we gave a ſhout.</l>
               <l>Who ſaid indeed it was great pitty,</l>
               <l>we ſhould be thus turn'd out.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Cromwell</hi> anſwered him again,</l>
               <l>and ſaid, t'was ſuch as he,</l>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:50469:67"/>
               <l>That were the Spunges of the land,</l>
               <l>and now muſt ſquezed be.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Which indeed in ſome caſe was not ſaid amiſſe, for he arrived at a very vaſt eſtate by being a Cuſtomer, and one of the Treaſurers for ſale of the King, Queen and Princeſſe Lands at <hi>VVorceſter</hi> houſe, and of the lands belonging to the pretended Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, at the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Houſe in <hi>Drury lane;</hi> beſides he compaſſed a conſiderable Eſtate out of the Lands of the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> at a very inconſiderable rate.</p>
            <p>He dyed much about the time with <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> at his aſſumed houſe at <hi>Fox-hall,</hi> and preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him dyed his Wife alſo, leaving their illegal and ill-gotten Eſtate to his Brother <hi>Deputy Allen</hi> a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald Painter in <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Heirs I doubt will have little cauſe to glory in it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:50469:68"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>Thomas Andrewes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ALderman <hi>Thomas Andrewes</hi> was at firſt a Linnen Draper upon <hi>Fiſh-ſtreet hill,</hi> but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved his Eſtate better by the times then by his Trade, for which purpoſe he was made a Treaſurer for Plate, Money, and one of the Treaſurers at War, for which he received three pence <hi>per</hi> pound; he was likewiſe one of the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for the Cuſtomes, and with his brother <hi>Allen</hi> was likew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe one of the Treaſures for ſale of the Lands of the late King, Queen and Prince, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe imployments being gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him, made him take any
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:50469:68"/> courſe to maintaine and propagate the power by which he received them, whereupon he ſides with the Kings Murtherers, and appears at that Court as one of his Judges, and at laſt ſignes likewiſe the Warrant for Execution,</p>
            <p>And now having had a hand in the King's bloud, he is reſolved to blot out the Name thereof. For in the year, 1649. Alderman <hi>Reynold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> in whoſe Mayoralty an Act was ſet on foot for the aboliſhing of Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and for the declaring our now Soveraigne, then Prince, a Traytor; which was Ordered to be proclaimed in the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> But honeſt Alderman <hi>Reynold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> refuſed to be preſent at that wicked Proclamation, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely and plainly told them, he would not publiſh any ſuch thing; and for ſuch his denyal, was fyned two thouſand pounds, and three
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:50469:69"/> months Impriſonment; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this, Alderman <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> accepts of the place of Maior in his abſence: proclaimes the Act againſt Kingly Government, and ſerves out the remaining part of Alderm. <hi>Reynoldſon</hi>'s Government, as if he had been legally choſen to doe the ſame, and the next yeare ſucceeding, was choſen himſelfe by the City, Lord Mayor of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He arrived at very little notice afterwards, unleſſe a Knighthood from the Protector, which he but little while enjoyed, although he was a principal Man at the proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Richard Cromwell</hi> after the Uſurpers Death.</p>
            <p>He had very many Children, moſt of his Sons got their Eſtates in Imployments under him, but never lived to enjoy them; for to his continued grief, he was hardly out of Mourning for one, before he had occaſion to mourne for the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:50469:69"/> loſſe of another; At laſt a Suit of law coming upon him for a wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully detain'd ſum of money which he injuriouſly kept in his hands of another Mans, he dyed ſuddenly full of years, in the Year 1659. and had he lived a Yeare longer, three that had been Lord Maiors of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in Twenty years time had held up their hands at the ſame Barre where they had Condemned many Wretched perſons which had not ſo much deſerved it as themſelves.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:50469:70"/>
            <head>The Life of Col. <hi>John Venn.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>COl. <hi>John Venn,</hi> was a Citizen of <hi>London</hi> likewiſe, and as I have heard a decaying Tradſman, he was taken notice of for his more then ordinary forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt the Kings intereſt; when the Wars increaſed, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Principles increaſed too, by reaſon whereof he was made Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>VVindſor,</hi> where he had the opportunity to encreaſe his Eſtate, not onely by the Plunder of the Countrey thereabouts, but by getting into his poſſeſſion much of the Kings houſhold ſtuff, Hangings, Linnen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He was a chief Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultator with the wicked Councel
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:50469:70"/> of the Army at <hi>VVindſor,</hi> and gave his Vote among them to Murther the King.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> afterwards Martyr'd, Chaplaine to his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who inſtructed him in better Principles then he afterwards pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and about the year, 1645, or 1646: this Col. <hi>Venn</hi> took a houſe in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet, London,</hi> for the onely reaſon that he might be near unto Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> who then preached at St. <hi>Annes</hi> Church, <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> not far from <hi>Venns</hi> Lodging; and about the year, 1647: this profeſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Collonel, being to remove from thence to a place called <hi>Brum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> near <hi>Kenſington,</hi> by reaſon of which diſtance he could not enjoy, as he pretended, the benefit of Mr <hi>Lov</hi>'s ſoul ſearching preaching, whereupon he hired the Author of this ſmall Treatiſe to be a conſtant Hearer of M. <hi>Love,</hi> and to take his Sermons in Short-writing, who
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:50469:71"/> made it his buſineſſe all the weeke following to tranſcribe them again into a legible hand, whereby what Mr. <hi>Love</hi> preach'd one Sunday at St. <hi>Anns,</hi> was the next Sunday re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preach'd by Col. <hi>Venn</hi> in his own Family. And yet this wretched Man acts contrary even to theſe Principles; in the year, 1648, he forſook both Mr. <hi>Love</hi> and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion too, and ſides with the then prevailing factious party, and is nominated one of the Judges of the King, who by this time they had contrived to put to Death, to the great affliction and more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary trouble of ſpirit of Mr. <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, he was one of the Judges of the King, and moſt impudently ſate among them; he ſigned like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to that blacke Authority that cauſed that unheard of Execution: and laſtly, he proved a great enemy to Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> whom formerly he ſo earneſtly thirſted after, and would
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:50469:71"/> not appeare to helpe him either in his Impriſonment, Confinements, or Death.</p>
            <p>But at laſt, he himſelfe was not much regarded, The judgements of God followed him in a troubled Conſcience; and at laſt, going to Bed very well with his wife, he was found dead by her the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; no perſons that were with him that night, nor his wife that lay by him, being in the leaſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his approaching end.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:50469:72"/>
            <head>The Life of Sir <hi>William Conſtable.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SIR <hi>VVilliam Conſtable,</hi> was one of thoſe who appeared eminently againſt Kingly power, he was a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel in the Parliaments Army, and a great Sider with the Sectarian part thereof; his Eſtate was enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for Debt, and he knew no way to recover his Decays but by ſaying and doing as thoſe wretches com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; He ſold his Eſtate to Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale</hi> for twenty thouſand pounds, and afterwards beggs it againe of the Parliament; for that as he ſaid Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale</hi> was a Delinquent, and ſo his Eſtate was in their Diſpoſe, his
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:50469:72"/> thus decay'd fortune made him <hi>ſide</hi> with the Conſpirers of the King's Death, and he was one of his Judges, and ſet his Hand and Seal for taking away the Life of the King, and did as much as in him lay for tranſplanting and removing the very Name &amp; memory thereof. He died in the Reigne of the laſt uſurping Tyrant that I pray <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may ever have.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:50469:73"/>
            <head>The Life of Sir <hi>John Danvers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SIR <hi>John Danvers</hi> was a Collonel in the ſaid Army, was Brother to the Earle of <hi>Danby,</hi> who he proved to be a Delinquent in that Rump-Parliament, whereby he might overthrow his will and ſo compaſſe the Eſtate himſelfe; he ſided likewiſe with the Sectarian party, was one of the King's Judges and lived afterwards ſome years in his ſin without repentance.</p>
            <p>But drawing near to his Death I have cauſe to believe that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of the wickedneſſe of his Life, for that, then Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> (now Dr.) <hi>Fuller</hi> was converſant in his Family and preached ſeverall
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:50469:73"/> times at Sir <hi>John Danver</hi>'s deſire in <hi>Chelſey</hi> Church, where I am ſure, all (that frequented that Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) will ſay he was inſtructed to repent of his miſguided and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Conſultations in having to doe with the Murther of that juſt Man. He died, (but how I cannot give an account) and hath no Queſtion received his Judgement.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:50469:74"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>Iſaac Ewer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>ISaac Ewer,</hi> began his Eſtate with the Wars, and increaſed therein according to the ſucceſſe thereof; he was a Colonel at <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Siege and there was at the Councell of War upon Sir <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> and Sir <hi>George Liſle,</hi> he was one of the Kings Judges, &amp; Signed the Warrant for the Murther; afterwards went with <hi>Cromwell</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> he was at that unheard of bloudy Quarter which was given to 4000 five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred accompliſht Men, at <hi>Tredagh</hi> in <hi>Ireland;</hi> where none in Armes eſcaped their Murther; although many of them laid down their Armes upon promiſe of their lives,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:50469:74"/> which notwithſtanding they Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; he was afterwards at the Siege of <hi>Clonmel</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and from thence at <hi>Waterford</hi> where the Town being taken he died ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly after of the Plague, and was there buried.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:50469:75"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>ANd thus you ſee how Evil purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe wicked Men, who thus thirſted after the bloud of their Soveraign; Nay, I ſay of one of the moſt Pious Princes as ever Ruled the Engliſh Scepter. A King who had no other fault but his too much Clemency, wherewith his nature did abound; whoſe Piety was as Tranſcendent as his Clemency, immoveable as the Rock which neither the unruly VVaves of Sedition impetuouſly breaking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, nor the Boyſterous and Irreſiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble winds of perſecution could work into the leaſt complyance, or diſturb in his reſolved ſtedfaſtneſs; one that like the Palme Tree that could flouriſh with the greater ſplendor by how much he
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:50469:75"/> was Preſt with ponderous inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and with our Saviour could bear the Croſſe with as much eaſe as he did his Crown, and improve his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions to the right uſe for which God Originally intended them, he could Spurne at the Glittering Glory of an Earthly Crown, and handling Chriſts Crown of Thornes could by the eye of Faith diſcern an immortal and eternal Crown of Glory.</p>
            <p>His Patience under Gods Afflicting hand was like that of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s farre above all that the world could doe to abuſe it, and not only ſo, but rejoycing in his Tribulation alſo. The Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment of his Body could not in the leaſt confine his mind, but rather give the greater advantages to his heavenly Soul for nearer and more deſired con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes with the King of Kings. No undutiful or unhandſome uſage which he received from the meaneſt of his People could Aggravate him into any paſſionate reflections, or exaſperate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:50469:76"/> the degree of his ſweet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placent Temper, he could not be wrought beyond the bounds of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, although he had to do with unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Men, nor was ever heard to uſe any expreſſions of Gaul and Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood towards thoſe that gave him Gaul and Vinegar to Drink; he bleſſed thoſe that curſed him, he prayed for thoſe that perſecuted him; and he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that thoſe who would not ſuffer him to live with them in his Earthly Kingdome, might be received with him into the Capacious Kingdome of Heavenly Glory.</p>
            <p>His Charity was as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall as that required from a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; <hi>viz.</hi> To the greateſt and moſt eminent of his forward Adverſaries; to thoſe who ſpit in his Face, he deſired that their Faces might ſhine with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction of the Spirit, and others who Vilifyed him with crying out <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Execution</hi> againſt him, he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that their ſinne might be forgiven,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:50469:76"/> and that they might not receive that Juſtice upon themſelves which they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for unjuſtly to be Executed upon him. Nay, and further, he did often declare that he did as freely forgive all the world with as much freedom as he did hope to be forgiven, and named one particular perſon among the reſt, ſaying, <hi>viz.</hi> I forgive <hi>Miles Corbet</hi> too, One who made it the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his ſtudy to ſtretch abuſed law, Arguments againſt the King, and aggravating the Kings demanding Juſtice againſt the Five Members with all the exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting circumſtances imaginable, which was the chief Original cauſe of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture civil and unhumane Bloudſhed, &amp; yet our moſt Pious and charitable Prince had charity even for this Man.</p>
            <p>His moderation was known unto all men, far above all mortal rules or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, take him which way you will, either as Man, a Chriſtian, or a KING, and in all three you ſhall find him to abound in his moderation; his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:50469:77"/> private Life as a Man was above the reach of envy to Tax him with any thing that might Blot or Staine his blameleſſe converſation; His Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity cauſed him to comply with the Peeviſh Precipitate Diſtempers of the times, hoping thereby to allay that furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fire which broke out among the Giddy headed People. And this our Gracious Soveraigne throwing the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his compaſſionate Chriſtianity thereon to quench it, it proved like water caſt on Lime, burn'd and ſmoak't with the greater Violence.</p>
            <p>His Kingly moderation far exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the other two, for he Stooped and Condiſcended even to things below himſelf, that he might let all the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rld ſee his readineſſe to comply with any thing that might gratifie their diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered and infatuated frenzy, which though nothing could do, he yet retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his aforeſaid ſerious and moderate temper; and having at that time to deal with a contradicting and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:50469:77"/> People, he moderately contrives all things, as much as in him lay, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile and make up their ruined and irrecoverable Breaches.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, His moderate Diet, his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance in all other affairs, his conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to his Queen, his fixed Religion, his heavenly Inclinations, his continued Devotions, his melting Clemeny, and his abuſed Charity, do all like ſo many Foiles ſhew the blackneſſe of that Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Action of Butchering ſuch a Pious Prince, the parallell of whom cannot be Sampled among the now Peaceable Kings of the Earth.</p>
            <p>In a word, His very Enemies could give him no worſe a caracter then what is contained in this, <hi>dimidium</hi> of his reall worth, which is repreſented but in dead colours, which no d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ubt but a more curious Pen will repreſent to it's lively Species. Some have ſaid (as <hi>Cornet Joyce</hi>) that if ever King of <hi>England</hi> went to Heaven, our Glorious Martyr King <hi>Charles</hi> did, who laid
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:50469:78"/> down his Life; and rather would lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his Prerogative, then the People ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> looſe their Priviledge. <hi>Oliver Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>well</hi> himſelf ſaid, that he was a vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe and Pious Man, but that he wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfortunate in his War. And <hi>Cook</hi> ſaid he was Wiſe and a Graciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prince, but that he muſt Dye, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy with him.</p>
            <p>And this was he whom theſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Men Sentenced to Death as a Murtherer, and a Traytor, whom Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels muſt acknowledge as one whoſe pure converſation might cauſe his Name to be Regiſtred in the Calanders of the Sainted Martyrs, valuing not ſo much his own, as the Lives and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Gentleman ſtanding at his ſad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terment, threw this Diſtick into the Vault.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Non Carolus magnus, nec Carolus quintus.</l>
               <l>Sed Carolus Agnus hic Jacet intus.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50469:78"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
